<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Houston Summer School on Dynamical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yunping Jiang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of participants in the workshop ``Houston Summer School on Dynamical Systems'' (HSSDY) for graduate students in late May or early June 2018. The 2018 HSSDY workshop will be held at the University of Houston. The 2018 HSSDY workshop will bring together roughly 40 graduate students from institutions across the country, who will attend the 9-day event, along with 10-15 exceptional undergraduates, who will arrive several days earlier and will receive a series of background lectures giving them some of the tools they need in order to attend the main event.  Additional information about the conference can be found on the website https://www.math.uh.edu/dynamics/school/school2018/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The HSSDY was funded by NSF from 2013 to 2017. The 2018 HSSDY workshop will continue the tradition of past workshops. The goal of the 2018 HSSDY workshop will introduce students both fundamental techniques and recent progress in dynamical systems. Moreover, the 2018 HSSDY workshop will introduce students the interrelationship between dynamical systems and other areas of mathematics and physics, including number theory, probability theory, statistical mechanics, and quantum information theory.  Each lecturer in the 2018 HSSDY workshop will give students an appropriate bird's-eye view of the area in which he/she is working.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1800669</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
