<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Workshop on Operator Theory and its Applications 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of participants in the meeting "International Workshop in Operator Theory and its Applications" (IWOTA) a workshop that will take place during July 23-27, 2018, on the campus of the East China Normal University in Shanghai, China. Additional information about the conference can be found on the website http://iwota2018.fudan.edu.cn&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2018 IWOTA meeting will continue the tradition of past meetings in this series going back to 1981. The meeting will be focused on the latest developments in functional analysis, specifically, operator theory and and related fields. This includes applications in engineering and mathematical physics from areas such as differential and integral equations, interpolation theory, system and control theory, signal processing, and scattering theory. The IWOTA meeting will run the week before the international symposium "Mathematical Theory of Networks and Systems"(MTNS) and this pairing provide opportunities for analysts to get exposed to engineering problems. Priority for funding will be given to early career mathematicians, women, members of underrepresented groups and those without other means of support. This is an important conference in operator theory and its applications that will offer participants the opportunity to learn of state-of-the-art research in operator theory with applications to engineering and other sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1800780</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
