<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Contextualizing Algebra for STEM Technicians</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>457409</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Virginia Carter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fewer than 40% of students who intend to major in STEM complete a STEM degree, and more than two-thirds of students pursuing STEM associate degrees do not complete their STEM programs within four years.  One barrier faced by prospective STEM majors is the failure to successfully complete the mathematics requirements. To address the mathematics barrier that impedes students' persistence and success in STEM associate degree technician programs, Lehigh Carbon Community College (LCCC) will redesign Intermediate Algebra and College Algebra to answer the question students continually ask: "Why do I need math?"&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematics faculty will work with an advisory committee of faculty and industry professionals from various engineering, technology, computing, and science fields to develop real-world applications that mimic those encountered in industry. Through multi-disciplinary, collaborative, and discovery-based learning, the students will increase their awareness of the relevance of algebra to STEM disciplines. It is expected that the revised mathematics courses will support an increase in the percentage of STEM students successfully passing algebra courses, and increase fall-to-fall retention in targeted STEM technician programs. The project has the potential to positively affect the teaching of algebra beyond LCCC. A professional development program will provide workshops for LCCC's full-time, part-time, and adjunct faculty and faculty at other colleges in the region and for secondary instructors who teach dual enrollment college algebra for high school students seeking college credit. Participants will receive kits of instructional materials to take back to their classrooms. A project website will be created to share the course materials and project results, and materials developed will be archived with ATE Central.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1801113</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Csikos</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ecsikos@lccc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sherrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Fenner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sfenner1@lccc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Werley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ewerley@lccc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh Carbon Community College</Name>
<CityName>Schnecksville</CityName>
<ZipCode>180782598</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107991585</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4525 Education Park Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
