<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Building Judicial Legitimacy or Inviting Institutional Backlash?</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>163929</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Democracy depends on popular will but also obedience to a rule of law ultimately prescribed by the Constitution. High courts are called on to be final arbiters of constitutional meaning. The Kenyan Supreme Court's invalidation of the August 2017 presidential election and directive for a new election in late October 2017 presents a crucial test of the Court's institutional legitimacy, or rightful authority to render constitutional and legal rulings for the polity. This project examines how the public has responded to this landmark ruling, as well as to the new election that the Court has ordered. Do citizens' ethnic and partisan affiliations drive their assessments of the Supreme Court's legitimacy in light of this landmark ruling? Or can perceptions of procedural fairness and other non-policy factors overcome ethnic or partisan bias and build a reservoir of legitimacy for the Court? These questions are incredibly important in an emerging democracy like Kenya with a high court that has a short institutional history. Mass and elite responses to the Court's actions will set a strong precedent for the future of the rule of law and democratic governance, not only in Kenya but in Africa writ large. Moreover, a history of mass public protests and violence in response to controversial elections makes understanding the public's response to this episode extremely important for theoretical, empirical, and normative reasons. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This project will test theoretical hypotheses centered on process-based (procedural fairness, subscription to democratic values) versus outcome-based (ethnic or partisan disagreement with Court outcomes) models of institutional legitimacy. These hypotheses with a two-wave national panel survey, which includes a survey experiment, of Kenyan citizens. Using an oversample of control group respondents from the first wave, descriptive statistics related to legitimacy and other Court-related assessments and examine the effects of process and outcome-based factors on legitimacy and other evaluations will be generated. A field experiment will also be conducted to allow identification of the causal effects of procedural fairness and elite cues, both countervailing and aligning with ethnopartisan preferences' on Supreme Court legitimacy. The experiment will also examine whether procedural fairness and countervailing elite cues can attenuate ethnopartisan bias in legitimacy judgments. Finally, the second wave survey will allow the identification of how different ethno-partisans' attitudes toward the Supreme Court change in light of the outcome of the new election.  Examining these changes will provide an additional test of the outcome-based model and examine how and whether reactions (both positive and negative) to the court?s decision persist into the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1801207</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Horowitz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeremy.horowitz@dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Kramon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ekramon@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Bartels</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bartels@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
