<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Formation of Ethnoracial Identity</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project investigates the processes by which children of new groups integrate into American society. More specifically, it focuses on the individual and group-level identity-formation processes central to their incorporation.  This study will expand knowledge of these fast-growing but little-studied groups, especially of how they are transitioning to new patterns of life.  Findings will advance understanding of identity formation and inform policy makers and educators concerned with the adaptation of new groups, and workers both outside and inside the groups whose goal is to ease their transitions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study uses ethnographic observations and interviews with high school students and teachers in the Bronx and Brooklyn to explore their integration experiences and the identity-formation processes central to their incorporation.  Semi-structured interviews will be conducted with 50 children from new groups plus, for comparison and contrast, 40 students from more established groups but generally matched on school performance and economic status.  In addition, 20 teachers and staff will be interviewed.  These interviews will be supplemented with ethnographic observations of classrooms, local recreation areas, and local commercial centers.  The data and contrasting perspectives will illuminate how ethnoracial identity may be formed and changed in a diverse environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1802599</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shamus</FirstName>
<LastName>Khan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sk2905@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dialika</FirstName>
<LastName>Sall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ds3276@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
