<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Probing Non-Coding RNA in Live Cells by Convertible Tetrahedral DNA</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>331191.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>331191</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ribonucleic acid (RNA) is a polymeric molecule essential in various biological roles in coding, decoding, regulation, and expression of genes. A non-coding RNA (ncRNA) is an RNA molecule that is not translated into a protein. Non-coding RNAs contribute to diseases including cancers, autism, and Alzheimer's. Non-coding (nc) RNAs, such as microRNA (miRNA) and long non-coding RNA (lncRNA), play pivotal roles in the regulation of various physiological and pathological processes. Nonetheless, the mechanistic&lt;br/&gt;regulation, subcellular distribution, and mode of action of ncRNAs remain elusive due to a lack of effective tools for probing ncRNAs in live cells. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will develope a multispectral single molecule barcode biosensor for dynamic multigene analysis. They will establish a convertible tetrahedral DNA (CTED) biosensor along with a multispectral single molecule sensing (MSMS) system for multiplex ncRNA detection in live cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1802947</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pak Kin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wong</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pak@engr.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
