<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Translational Data Science - Industry / Academic Confluence (TDS-IAC)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48248.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48248</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the increased availability, prominence, and applicability of data in all of our lives, the emerging&lt;br/&gt;field of Translational Data Science is critical to harnessing societal benefit from advances in data-related&lt;br/&gt;scientific disciplines. The unprecedented growth in the creation and use of data offers new opportunities&lt;br/&gt;for fostering more effective bridges between researchers, industry and government colleagues, and a&lt;br/&gt;diverse community to enable new scientific progress and tangible advances for societal benefit.  This workshop will focus on academic research and industry expertise to further cooperation and partnerships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Translational data science is an emerging field that applies data science principles, techniques, and&lt;br/&gt;technologies to scientific challenges that hold the promise of having an important societal impact. It&lt;br/&gt;focuses on the interface and interactions between foundational aspects of data science and their use in&lt;br/&gt;advancing scientific frontiers. By convening a diverse community of stakeholders who can contribute to the strategic development of a Translational Data Science roadmap, this workshop will build and strengthen connections across sectors. The perspectives and insights shared from industry, government, nonprofits, and academia, coupled with discussions focused on actionable challenges and measurable outcomes, will serve to advance the field of data science as well as related fields and application areas. The workshop provides a mechanism for identifying high-priority topics and high-impact opportunities for future research, training, and collaboration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1802878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Culler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>culler@cs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dugan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jmdugan@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
