<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Participant Support for a GSA Thompson Field Forum: Processes controlling the growth and evolution of continental batholiths, Coast Mountains British Columbia Canada</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21810.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21810</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal provides support for student participation and early career faculty to participate in a Geological Society of Geological Society of America Thompson Field Forum entitled." Participants of the forum will examine important field relationships along a transect across the Coast Mountains batholith between Terrace and Prince Rupert Canada that will be held August 12 to 17, 2018. Along with the field trip, evening technical sessions will involve talks and discussion regarding processes of magmatism, continental growth, and collisional, accretionary, and translational tectonics. The Coast Mountains Batholith, British Columbia is an ideal location for forum because is one of the largest magmatic complexes on earth and it exhibits significant along strike and cross strike variations in structure, compostion, and depths from which the rocks have been exhumed. In particular, the forum will examine the concept of high flux magmatic events. A growing body of data from upper and lower crustal exposure of batholiths around the globe indicate that most batholiths are comprised of intrusions that are emplaced during relatively brief time periods (tens of millions of years) known as High Flux Events (HFE). Field stops and discussions will focus on locations that are important for discerning mechanisms that trigger these high flux magmatic events. Specific topics to be addressed during the forum include 1) What are the sources for batholith magmas; 2) What are the triggering mechanisms for high flux magmatic events; and 3) What is the magnitude and significance of large-scale translational faulting on batholith architecture? Support for this forum will provide assistance for ten students and early career faculty to attend and benefit from this unique activity. The travel and logistical support for the forum will directly enhance science education in an important STEM discipline through the participants increased awareness and ability to integrate field, analytical, and model based science. Participants will be in an excellent position to disseminate these ideas to the research community and the general public, and the experience will greatly enhance their future scientific careers. A publicly available document describing field stops and related geological syntheses will be produced by the Geological Society of America.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1802136</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
<LastName>Stowell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hstowell@geo.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
