<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference Proposal: Automorphic Forms on Reductive Groups and Their Covers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support the participation of early-career, US-based researchers at the workshop "Automorphic forms on Reductive Groups and their Covers" to be held June 25-28, 2018 at the FIM Institute for Mathematical Research, at ETH Zuerich in Zurich, Switzerland. The conference will focus on recent advances in automorphic forms and automorphic representations, particularly those related to covering (metaplectic) groups. Participating researchers are from the US, Israel, Europe, South Korea, and Singapore.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Automorphic forms and automorphic representations are topics with historical origins in number theory, but recent advances have led to new and surprising connections with mathematical physics. A particular theme of the conference will be the uses of small automorphic representations in both number theory and string theory. The web site for the conference may be found at https://www.math.ethz.ch/fim/conferences/friedberg.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1802887</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
