<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Equilibria of Two Relaxed Plasma Species With One Species Confined by the Space Charge of the Other Species</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>186000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>186000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There are many areas of scientific research that may benefit from the development of improved plasma confinement and control methods.  These include studies of antimatter, charged particle beams, and non-neutral plasmas.  The goal of this project is to develop a theoretical understanding of the conditions for a plasma of one species of charged particles to be confined by an electric field produced by a plasma of a second species of charged particles.  The project provides training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, including members of traditionally underrepresented groups in science and engineering.  The work will be carried out by students as part of their research training and will be supervised by the principal investigator to assure professional quality, with research results presented in peer-reviewed journals and at technical conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will explore the equilibrium of a two-species plasma, with one plasma species confined by the space charge of the other; with the outer species confined by using the concept of an artificially structured boundary in a cylindrical geometry. Conditions for achieving an equilibrium in which a neutral region forms with each species having the same temperature is sought. This plasma confinement approach is intended to provide a highly quiescent plasma.  The theoretical understanding will be developed using classical trajectory Monte Carlo, Poisson-Boltzmann finite difference, and particle-in-cell numerical methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1803047</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Ordonez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cao@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
