<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Georgia Discrete Analysis Conference</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19942.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19942</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Georgia Discrete Analysis Conference will be held on May 14-17, 2018, at the University of Georgia in Athens, Georgia. The purpose of the meeting is to exchange ideas related to the latest developments in discrete analysis with a focus on those in arithmetic combinatorics. Special emphasis will be placed on new or evolving directions for research. Arithmetic combinatorics, broadly defined, is an area of research that deals with combinatorial structures involving the basic operations of addition and multiplication and their interactions. Though its problems are often purely combinatorial their solutions often incorporate techniques from analysis, combinatorics, and number theory. The meeting will be at an international level, with many world renowned speakers. The organizers plan to invite 14 speakers (four of which will be early career mathematicians) and at least 35 additional participants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topics to be cover at the Georgia Discrete Analysis Conference include: pseudorandomness and its various manifestations in number theory and combinatorics, Gowers' uniformity norms, recent developments related to Roth's and Szemeredi's and the Green-Tao theorem, the sum-product phenomena and incidence theorems. Many of these topics have witnessed a flurry of recent activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference webpage: research.franklin.uga.edu/additive-combinatorics/georgia-discrete-analysis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1804049</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
