<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Complex Differential Geometry</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12570.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12570</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Shanks Workshop on Complex Differential Geometry will take place on March 2-3, 2018, at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN. The workshop brings together leading researchers with different backgrounds, but common research  interests in the area of complex differential geometry. This research area uses techniques from complex analysis, differential geometry and algebraic geometry, and the real insight of these theories is highlighted when all these facets merge together and relations between them are established. The main goal of the workshop is to promote these interactions and initiate new projects and collaborations. This meeting is expected to be highly beneficial to graduate students and junior mathematicians as they will have the opportunity to interact with experts in the field in a friendly, open to discussions environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Complex differential geometry is an area with deep roots and very rapid and diverse advances. The proposed workshop brings together researchers using a variety of techniques which focus on one main problem: understanding canonical metrics in complex geometry. The workshop is intended to present recent progress in the study of complete Calabi-Yau manifolds and Ricci solitons with prescribed asymptotic behavior, Sasaki-Einstein geometry, extremal Kahler metrics, moduli space of Kahler metrics and the relations with stability, and generalizations to Hermitian geometry. For more details, see the workshop webpage at https://my.vanderbilt.edu/shankscdg/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1804586</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
