<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Femtosecond laser surgery in the ablation cooling regime for improved depth and speed</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will study the physical effects of ultra-fast lasers operating in the 'ablation-cool' regime, where the short laser pulses operate at a very high pulse rep-rate so that the pulses occur before the heat is dissipated in the tissue. This can overcome the difficulties that result from laser-cutting tissue at the normal low rep-rates. The advantages include enhanced efficiency of cutting, improved removal-rates of products material, use of lower powers, and allowing deeper penetration depths. This will have a pronounced impact on the operation in systems where fine-tuning of accuracy of surgery, deep tissue penetration, and product removal are critical, such as vocal cords lesions or spine surgeries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project utilizes a burst-mode femtosecond laser system that would deliver pulses at nearly 1.5 GHz rate leading to high energy deposited into the target area. The investigators hypothesize that such a burst mode GHz train of pulses would result in a deeper sub-surface ablation. The PIs further predict that such a pulse train will lead to an order-of-magnitude increase in ablation rates compared to conventional kHz repetition rate femtosecond lasers, in addition to avoiding thermal side effects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1805998</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adela</FirstName>
<LastName>Ben-Yakar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ben-yakar@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
