<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on Algebras, Representations, and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference "Algebras, Representations, and Applications" will be held at  Universidad Nacional San Antonio Abad de Cusco in Peru from August 27 to August 31, 2018. This conference is a satellite conference for the 2018 International Congress of Mathematicians that will bring together mathematicians from all over the world. This award will provide support for US-based participants with priority given to participants from under-represented groups and early-career researchers. The conference lectures will be in a colloquium style in order to make the material accessible to post-doctoral scholars and graduate students. There will also be short communication sessions consisting of 30-minute talks delivered by early-carrier mathematicians. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The representation theory of Lie algebras and related algebraic structures has become a comprehensive and mainstream research area in mathematics. In particular, new categorical and geometric constructions have taken the lead not only within Lie theory, but also in other areas of mathematics and physics such as combinatorics, group theory, number theory, integrable systems, partial differential equations, topology and conformal field theory. Recent developments in representation theory using D-modules, Koszul duality, Hodge theory, and higher category are strengthening these interactions further. The conference will cover a wide range of these developments and their applications. The aim of the conference is to bring together leading specialists to discuss  the major achievements of the last decade in algebras and representation theory, as well as problems and fundamental conjectures that continue to abound the area.  Further details can be found at the conference website https://sites.google.com/view/icm2018satellitecusco/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1805763</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
