<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Testing Spacetime Symmetry Foundations of General Relativity</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>89810.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24642</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Modern physics rests on two widely successful theories: Einstein's General Relativity (GR) and quantum physics.  The former describes all known gravitational phenomena on scales larger than micrometers, the latter describes the atomic and subatomic world.  Physicists widely conjecture that the two are merged in an as yet unknown unified theory.  Much recent work in the literature has revealed the possibility that observable hints of such a unified theory could arise as violations of the foundations of General Relativity theory, including local Lorentz symmetry, which encapsulates the principles of Special Relativity.  These studies will investigate new types of signals for Lorentz violation in experiments and observations ranging from Earth laboratory experiments to distant pulsar observations and gravitational waves.  Undergraduate research projects and outreach opportunities are planned in this proposal.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The supported work will make use of an effective field theory framework for describing generic spacetime-symmetry violation that has been widely adopted in recent years.  A significant part of the work will involve phenomenology and analysis in precision Solar-system tests of gravity including Earth-laboratory tests and space-based tests.  Building on prior work, the PI will also further develop the effective field theory framework in the area of beyond solar-system astrophysics and apply the results to gravitational waves and observations of pulsar systems.  The PI will also investigate the match of specific proposed models, used widely in the literature, to this test framework with the goal of constraining these models with existing and future measurements.  By providing motivation and additional areas in which to search for new physics beyond GR, this work will positively impact researchers involved in precision tests of GR in Earth laboratories, solar-system tests, and those working on gravitational wave observations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1806871</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
