<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Assessment of Hurricane Marias impact and subsequent effects of ecosystem regeneration and heavy metal inputs in an urban coastal wetland</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Santiago</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Nation Science Foundation-supported Center for Innovation, Research and Education in Environmental Nanotechnology at the University of Puerto Rico - Rio Piedras is dedicated to the development of nanomaterials and devices to address environmental pollution, while developing a diverse science, technology, engineering and mathematics workforce.  The Center's research endeavors include development of nanomaterials for water purification, soil remediation, and resource recovery. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Center investigators submitted a Rapid Response (RAPID) proposal to the National Science Foundation to conduct quick-response research on a natural disaster. The combined paths of Hurricane Irma on September 6, 2017, and Hurricane Maria on September 20, 2017, had devastating effects across the entire island of Puerto Rico. The urban coastal wetland that serves as the Center testbed, source of substrates for nanostructure development, and substrate for biofuel production, was severely affected by the hurricane winds, and by massive flooding due to fresh water flowing from upland sources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Center research staff at the University of Puerto Rico Rio Piedras will (1) assess hurricane impact and subsequent wetland regeneration: the substrate source for nanostructure construction, substrate source for biofuel generation, and the plant species to be used in combination with nanostructures for nano-phyto remediation work, and (2) quantify the heavy metal inputs to the testbed wetland.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT: &lt;br/&gt;Proposed research will contribute to knowledge concerning the impact of extraordinary natural climatological events, such as a massive hurricane and the subsequent climatological conditions in the area, impact regeneration dynamics of an urban coastal wetland system, and its capacity for heavy metal remediation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT: &lt;br/&gt;Proposed work will advance discovery and understanding of how massive hurricane impacts affect coastal wetlands under a framework of urban and industrial conditions. Project activities provide hands-on training and learning, by involving graduate and undergraduate students in research. The project will broaden the participation of under-represented groups in science technology, engineering and mathematics fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1806129</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elvira</FirstName>
<LastName>Cuevas</LastName>
<EmailAddress>epcuevas@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Ortiz-Zayas</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jorgeortiz.ites@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico-Rio Piedras</Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<ZipCode>009252512</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7877634949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>18 Ave. Universidad, Ste.1801</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
