<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Center for Advancing the Societal Impacts of Research</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5221393.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2421393</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bernice Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Center for Advancing the Societal Impacts of Research (CASIR) will advance the rigor, relevance, and practice of broader impacts (BI) by  (a) cultivating and strengthening the existent and emerging BI expert community; (b) building capacity of researchers and educators to enhance and articulate the broader impacts of their work; and (c) creating socio-technical infrastructure able to adapt to stakeholder needs as BI continues to grow and evolve. CASIR builds on the foundational work of the National Alliance for Broader Impacts and will advance the practice of translating scientific research for public understanding and meet the growing demand for innovative BI training and resources. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The Center will develop resources and provide professional development to diverse audiences across multiple institution types and settings, including research-intensive universities, minority-serving institutions, technical and community colleges, and primarily undergraduate institutions in the jurisdictions of the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research.  CASIR will directly enhance BI capacity at the individual, departmental, institutional, and national levels. Particular focus will be given to individual researchers and institutions representing and serving traditionally under-served populations.  In addition, CASIR will facilitate dialogue and collaboration around evidence-based approaches to enhancing, evaluating, and documenting research impacts. Overall, the work will be valuable to the community of researchers driving discovery, the community of professionals who provide BI support and collaboration with researchers, and the public which stands to benefit from research and education projects that are well-designed and executed in a way that enhances their broader impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF-wide support for this Center augments the Foundation's current efforts to educate research communities about the importance of the broader impacts criterion in the review process and to communicate the societal benefits of fundamental science and engineering research.  CASIR's emphasis on documentation, evidence, and best practices will support an evidence-building approach to investing in discovery and innovation. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This award is co-funded by the Office of Integrative Activities (OIA) and the following Directorates:  Biological Sciences (BIO), Computer and Information Science and Engineering (CISE), Education and Human Resources (EHR), Engineering (ENG), Geosciences (GEO), Mathematical and Physical Sciences (MPS), and Social, Behavioral, and Economic Sciences (SBE).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1810732</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Rover</LastName>
<EmailAddress>drover@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonnell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mcdonnel@marine.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Niemi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kjniemi@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Renoe</LastName>
<EmailAddress>renoes@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Risien</LastName>
<EmailAddress>julie.risien@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1397</Code>
<Text>Cross-Directorate  Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7261</Code>
<Text>Project &amp; Program Evaluation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7550</Code>
<Text>Eval &amp; Assessment Capabilites</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>ICER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
