<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support to attend The 16th International Heat Transfer Conference (Beijing, China, August 10-15, 2018)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The International Heat Transfer Conference has a long and rich history, which dates back to the International Discussion on Heat Transfer held in London and Atlantic City in 1951. In 1966, with the third conference held in Chicago, the International Heat Transfer Conference started a four-year cycle, having been organized already in 16 different cities of 9 countries. As the world's premier thermal transport processes conferences, researchers, engineers and scientists from all over the world get together to exchange knowledge and experience and introduce novel interdisciplinary research ideas. The International Heat Transfer Conference continues the increasingly important mission of fostering international cooperation and the exchange of ideas among scientists and engineers in the heat and mass transfer research community, together with engaging underrepresented minorities in its activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International Heat Transfer Conference is the largest worldwide forum on heat transfer and thermal science and engineering. The organization is devoted to meeting the scientific and social challenges of thermal energy usage, environmental sustainability, materials processing, and bioscience. The mission of International Heat Transfer Conference has become more important with the rapid development of human society. The International Heat Transfer Conference will be held in Beijing, China, August 10-15, 2018. It is under the auspices of the Assembly for International Heat Transfer Conferences, an institution founded in 1966, with the principal goal of creating and sustaining a worldwide forum for heat transfer specialists to present research results, discuss the state of the art techniques in heat transfer areas, and identify the future direction and priorities in the various domains of thermal science and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1811794</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiuling</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wangx@pnw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
