<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: JUNO2: Resilient Edge Cloud Designed Networks</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449089.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149966</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Von Lehmen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Achieving trustworthy IoT(Internet of Things) and CPS(Cyberphysical Systems) for Smart and Connected Communities (SCC) is both an important goal and a major challenge.  The objective of this project is to address that challenge by leveraging a resilient edge cloud network--computing capabilities that are networked together and reside close to the end user and critical applications -- to enable fast response, scalability to a large number of applications, and fail-safe operation.  The project will conduct collaborative and foundational research with collaborators in Japan, on a resilient edge cloud network to achieve basic understanding of the underlying science for future networks. The approach includes virtualized adaptable computing and networking, consideration of resource constraints, potential mobility of end devices/sensors and security.  The results from this project will advance more resilient network-compute infrastructure for SCC applications such as smart health, smart transportation, smart energy, etc.  The Japanese-US collaboration provides an international testbed for demonstrating the project approach. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to improve the performance of IoT/CPS by realizing a resilient distributed edge cloud network architecture. The objective is to provide (1) coverage extension by introducing spatio-temporal floating edge cloud (EC) function over end devices; (2) resilient communication between end-devices and edge clouds via interface diversity and flow-based control; (3) optimal resource allocation among end-device, EC, and backend cloud (BC) to meet diverse quality-of-service requirements such as latency and blocking rate; (4) designing a spatially and temporally optimized and dynamically adjustable utilization of virtual network links and virtual machines (5) bio-inspired intrusion detection system for protecting IoT/CPS devices (5) distributed database using hypercube. The project will leverage the SmartCity testbed in New York and the StarBED4 testbed in Japan, which is a large-scale emulation/simulation infrastructure consisting of 1,000 servers.  These will be integrated into a single testbed for large-scale real and emulation experiments, and will be accessible to both US and Japanese researchers on this project.  The networks will be connected via global research networks i.e., Internet2 and NYSERNET in US, and JGN and SINET in Japan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1818884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tarek</FirstName>
<LastName>Saadawi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>saadawi@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abbe</FirstName>
<LastName>Mowshowitz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>abbe@cs.ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myung</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lee@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Akira</FirstName>
<LastName>Kawaguchi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>akira@cs.ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7071</Code>
<Text>JUNO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
