<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Catalyst Award: Integration of Biotechnology and Cyberinstruction in the Biological Sciences at Fort Valley State University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. Through this one-year project, Fort Valley State University seeks to redesign/upgrade its curricula to integrate biotechnology, genomics and cyber-infrastructure [Anywhere, Anytime Learning]. The proposed project will invigorate existing courses by integrating biotechnology applications into the curriculum and pedagogical practices. Cyberinfrastructure and learning will also be infused in laboratory activities, in which bioinformatics tools are used.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project goal is to redesign and integrate biotechnology and cyberinfrastructure components into core courses, specifically Biotechniques, Cell &amp; Molecular Biology and Genetics. This will provide students with an in-depth understanding of the cycle of scientific problem solving, the nature of iterative experimental design and the role of an adaptive approach that will uniquely prepare them for graduate study or the biotechnology workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1818695</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seema</FirstName>
<LastName>Dhir</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Dhirs@fvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Shakespeare</LastName>
<EmailAddress>shakespearet@fvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Celia</FirstName>
<LastName>Dodd</LastName>
<EmailAddress>doddc@fvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Fort Valley State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Valley</CityName>
<ZipCode>310304313</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4788256253</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1005 State University Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>061Z</Code>
<Text>Life STEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
