<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Shared Facilities Operations Workshop 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71863.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71863</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2018 Shared Facilities Operations Workshop will serve to assemble a group of Senior Investigators and Staff Scientists/Facilities Managers to discuss critical issues in the running of Shared Facilities, particularly as they pertain to the advancement of the materials research infrastructure in the United States. The participants will be drawn from projects supported by three different National Science Foundation Division of Materials Research programs: The Materials Research Science and Engineering Centers (MRSEC), the Partnerships for Research and Education in Materials (PREM), and the Materials Innovation Platforms (MIP). The Intellectual Merit of the proposed Workshop is based on the anticipated outcomes of how Shared Facilities at universities can be run more efficiently to advance materials research and innovation. In particular, there will be a focus on how instrumentation distributed across the country can be most effectively and efficiently employed in a manner that avoids the establishment of redundant instrumentation. The Broader Impacts of the proposed Workshop include making freely available all of the presentations and discussion notes of the Workshop to interested parties, including the suggestions of best practices for how to run efficient Shared Facilities that help university and industry researchers advance the gamut from fundamental understanding and readying products for the marketplace.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1818957</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ram</FirstName>
<LastName>Seshadri</LastName>
<EmailAddress>seshadri@mrl.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1736</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS CENTERS &amp; EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
