<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Impact Technology Exchange (HI-TEC) 2018: Deepening Engagement and Strengthening Connections</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>233495.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>277078</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Virginia Carter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In 2009, several Centers funded through the Advanced Technological Education (ATE) program worked collaboratively to develop a conference that would broaden the impact across ATE supported industry areas. This annual High-Impact Technology (HI-TEC) conference has drawn participants mainly from the ATE program's community of centers and projects. The activities proposed for this project will open new opportunities nationwide for the ATE centers to broaden their impact and develop new networks of project and industry collaborators in their areas of technology focus. This broadening can increase the impact of ATE projects across the nation and strengthen the American economy in high-demand fields that drive our most competitive industries. The proposed project will also strengthen HI-TEC's ability to help address issues faced in technological education everywhere. Examples of such cross-cutting issues include recruitment of diverse and underserved student populations, integration of research into the classroom, faculty development techniques, and best practices in education/industry partnerships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of the 2018 conference is "Partnering with Industry for the New American Workforce." The proposed activities would build upon HI-TEC's record of success to accomplish three goals: 1) Expand engagement in the conference by industry, ATE projects, and faculty engaged in advanced technological education who may not be currently supported by the ATE program; 2) Strengthen actionable connections between ATE projects and centers and others associated with the ATE community; and 3) Deepen sharing and broaden implementation of evidence-based models and best practices used by ATE projects and centers. These activities will be conducted within the framework of HI-TEC's existing structure, and will strengthen HI-TEC's impact nationally and, in turn, strengthen the impact of ATE centers and projects. This project will develop two new opportunities for participant engagement at the conference: the Technological Education Forum (TEF) and the Industry Partnerships Forum (IPF). Educators and industry personnel will learn from each other and collaborate to address issues facing advanced technological education. The conference's design, which stresses pedagogy, technology, program building, and workforce development, provides a unique professional development opportunity that enables educators to acquire new knowledge and skills. The evaluation activities will focus on both short-term outcomes and medium-term performance-based outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1818985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Lesiecki</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mlesiecki@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hope</FirstName>
<LastName>Cotner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hcotner@cord.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CORD</Name>
<CityName>Waco</CityName>
<ZipCode>767105841</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2547418334</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4901 Bosque Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
