<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Novel Immuno-Nutrition Properties of a Single Cell Protein to Abate Soy-Induced Enteritis in Aquafeeds</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to develop a protein replacement for soy-based marine animal diets to improve yield through effective nutrition and enhanced animal welfare. Aquafeeds represent &gt;50% of the cost of production, and losses due to mortality can be as high as 50% in certain commercial species. A novel feed ingredient that contains immuno-nutritional properties to address these inefficiencies could be considered a game-changer to the industry. Fish are the most resource-efficient sources of animal protein, a healthy source of food for people, and will be one of the ways to address food security. As the surface of the planet is greater than two-thirds ocean, one estimate suggests, if managed properly, just 2% of this vast resource could produce enough food for all of mankind. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to expand previous studies that suggested a novel single cell protein (SCP) is a significant candidate to serve as a fishmeal alternative. In addition, SCP also may contain functional properties that improve growth performance and survival. The SCP tested previously supported improved feed conversion ratios (FCR) as compared to conventional diets, while at the same time, statistically relevant improvements in survival of carnivorous fish and shrimp.  It also was observed that SCP relieved secondary disease complications associated with diets, such as gastro-enteritis. With hundreds of marketable species in aquaculture, and an industry that is just 50 years old, the collective understanding of aquatic animal nutrition is in its infancy. In this project, a carnivorous Seriola species will be used as a model organism to serve as an additional reference point beyond salmon. Targeted components of the SCP will be enhanced (or deleted) to determine the effect of leading immuno-nutritional candidates on the animals' ability to digest more completely inputs like soy bean meal (SBM). The effectiveness of SCPs in emerging commercial fish diets has yet to be fully elucidated, and the results of this study may have implications towards lower-cost feed formulations and optimized nutrition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1819652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Feinberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lfeinberg@knipbio.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>KnipBio Inc</Name>
<CityName>Harvard</CityName>
<ZipCode>014511501</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4136278149</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>142 Still River Rd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
