<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Flexible Krylov Subspace Projection Methods for Inverse Problems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>306589</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Miao-Jung Ou</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In many scientific and engineering applications, it is necessary to&lt;br/&gt;solve an inverse problem; that is, to determine quantities defining an&lt;br/&gt;object or a system through indirect measurements.  The mathematics&lt;br/&gt;used to produce images in devices such as X-Ray Computed Tomography&lt;br/&gt;(CT) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) are excellent examples.  The&lt;br/&gt;mathematical models describing an inverse problem are often so&lt;br/&gt;complicated that it is not possible to find an exact analytical&lt;br/&gt;solution, and it is necessary to use an approximation based on a set&lt;br/&gt;of simpler equations.  However, many equations may be needed; in&lt;br/&gt;medical imaging, for example, it is not unusual to compute&lt;br/&gt;approximations by solving millions of equations.  Additional&lt;br/&gt;complications arise because an inverse problem may have infinitely&lt;br/&gt;many solutions, or the solutions may change dramatically if there are&lt;br/&gt;small errors in the indirect measurements.  Thus, additional&lt;br/&gt;constraints and mathematical tools (often referred to as&lt;br/&gt;regularization) are needed to narrow the search to a set of&lt;br/&gt;appropriate feasible solutions, and to stabilize the computations.&lt;br/&gt;The type and amount of regularization is problem dependent, requiring&lt;br/&gt;the algorithms to be able to easily adapt to user and/or problem&lt;br/&gt;specifications.  The aim of this project is develop a flexible and&lt;br/&gt;adaptable computational platform that can be used for this important&lt;br/&gt;class of problems, which arise in many application areas, including&lt;br/&gt;space object identification, geophysics, microscopy and medical&lt;br/&gt;imaging. Thus advancements made from this project have the potential to&lt;br/&gt;benefit national defense, energy exploration, and human health.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Efficient iterative methods to compute regularized solutions of&lt;br/&gt;large-scale discrete ill-posed inverse problems will be developed.&lt;br/&gt;The approach will use flexible Krylov subspace iterative methods, and&lt;br/&gt;will exploit low-rank structure of data, solutions and operators. The&lt;br/&gt;approach will allow to incorporate a variety of regularization&lt;br/&gt;techniques, including sparse and low-rank constraints on the solution.&lt;br/&gt;The methods developed in this project can be used as tools to obtain&lt;br/&gt;approximate solutions of ill-posed inverse problems, and optimized&lt;br/&gt;implementations will be included in a new MATLAB package called IR&lt;br/&gt;Tools (Iterative Regularization Tools).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1819042</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Nagy</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jnagy@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
