<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of a textile-based retrievable stent for stroke that can be personalized to a patient's clot burden and retrieve long clots using torsion.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>221700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research&lt;br/&gt;(SBIR) project is significant as it offers a disruptive new mechanical approach to stroke&lt;br/&gt;treatment. Each year, 795,000 strokes occur in the U.S., 1.7 million strokes in Europe, and&lt;br/&gt;nearly 20.5 million strokes worldwide. This public-private partnership is expected to have an&lt;br/&gt;important positive societal impact on the community by saving lives especially the elderly and&lt;br/&gt;decreasing the economic burden of stroke on the taxpayer. This life-saving device has a unique&lt;br/&gt;value proposition for health-systems with lower inventory costs from a single size device, and&lt;br/&gt;for patients with better vessel re-opening rates, thereby saving brain cells. This textile-based&lt;br/&gt;braided retrievable stent, also known as an embolus retriever or thrombectomy-assist device is&lt;br/&gt;an innovation that will enhance scientific and technological understanding of how personalized&lt;br/&gt;medicine can transform the care of stroke patients in the U.S. and worldwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to bring to market the industry?s longest blood clot&lt;br/&gt;or embolus retriever for removal of short and long clots that can be customized by the operator&lt;br/&gt;based on each patient?s clot burden. In addition, it is the first textile-based braided retrievable&lt;br/&gt;stent which works well in conjunction with standard catheter-based aspiration systems for stroke&lt;br/&gt;treatment developed in the U.S. that can be personalized to all clot lengths. Stroke is a major&lt;br/&gt;problem causing 5.5 million deaths worldwide and currently there is no cost-effective and&lt;br/&gt;efficacious treatments. The mean lifetime healthcare cost per stroke patient is $140,048. This&lt;br/&gt;textile-based clot retrieval device (aka thrombectomy-assist device) is a cost-effective medical&lt;br/&gt;device that can help save a stroke patient?s life. The methods and approaches of this project is&lt;br/&gt;to compare via pre-clinical tests the ability of a textile-based medical device to re-open vessels&lt;br/&gt;blocked with clots compared with existing approved treatments. The goals and scope of the&lt;br/&gt;research will focus on the ability to rapidly re-open vessels that are blocked by clots. This paves&lt;br/&gt;the way for personalized medicine with a customizable stroke treatment device that can be&lt;br/&gt;tailored to a patient?s clot burden.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1819491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vallabh</FirstName>
<LastName>Janardhan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vallabh@inseratherapeutics.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Insera Therapeutics Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Sacramento</CityName>
<ZipCode>958351637</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9168490945</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1560 Arcola Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
