<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Soft Foam Polyurethanes from Algae Oil</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to create sustainable and biodegradable polyurethane products made from algae oils. Algae-based polymer precursors will be developed and used to produce finished polyurethane product with the desired physical characteristics. Development of polyurethane shoe soles will be targeted, including polyurethane flip-flops, as these are products where consumers are increasingly demanding the incorporation of sustainable materials and where the consumer is willing to pay the small extra cost associated with incorporating renewable materials. Developing algae polymers and high value products made from these will allow us to develop a novel monomer toolbox based on these bio-materials and to create new polymers with physical properties equal or superior to petroleum based polymers. These algae based polymers also provide cleaner, smarter products- pollution prevention at the molecular level. The development of environmentally sustainable and biodegradable products will reduce waste, prevent costly end-of-life remediation, lead to safer products and save energy and water resources. The development of these algae based polymer products will enable renewable materials to supplant petroleum-based materials while maintaining the performance characteristics of polyurethane products that consumers have come to appreciate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop sustainable monomers from bio-based algae feedstocks that will be used to create finished polyurethane soft foams that have the appropriate properties for shoe soles. It incorporates the preparation of algae-based polyols from multiple algae oil sources, going from bench to production scale, followed by formulation of these monomers into materials that meet the demands of a discerning eco-conscious consumer. The developed algae polyols will not be formulaic direct drop-in replacements for the corresponding petroleum sourced materials' careful formulation will be required to generate polyurethanes with the desired final product properties, and that are also compatible with current manufacturing techniques. Formulation and process compatibility are key steps, as industrial users are not looking to significantly modify manufacturing processes to incorporate new starting materials. Lastly, physical evaluation of the resulting polyurethanes will be done by comparing the performance metrics between bio and petroleum-based polyurethanes typically used by end users in sportswear and automotives. Using polyols derived from multiple algal strains, a polyurethane formulation for soft foams will be developed to demonstrate our ability to integrate product development and manufacturing, from sustainable feedstock and green chemistry through commercial application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1820277</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Tessman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mtessman@algenesismaterials.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ALGENESIS CORPORATION</Name>
<CityName>Cardiff by the Sea</CityName>
<ZipCode>920071438</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7607077930</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1238 Sea Village Dr</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
