<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Low-cost real-time perception system for self-driving consumer cars</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the practical deployment of a low-cost and low-power real-time perception system in self-driving consumer cars. This edge computing functionality in sensors enables higher reliability and lower cost of overall sensing and computing needed for truly autonomous self-driving. Such innovation will contribute significantly to the early and widespread availability of safety and convenience benefits to consumers. Furthermore, the advanced perception system will have a potential long-term impact on robotics in general, which can lead to creation of new markets and new lifestyles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop efficient algorithms and software implementation of a real-time perception system to enable the use of low-cost computing systems for self-driving cars. The algorithms provide a novel way of using image features to perform simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM) with 100 times less computational costs than the existing algorithms. They also include a truly novel neural network to fuse the image feature and light detection and ranging (LiDAR) features and perform object detection, which has 100 times less complexity compared to the state-of-the-art method. These reduced-complexity algorithms can be implemented on low-power and low-cost SoC processors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1820462</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Koji</FirstName>
<LastName>Seto</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kojiseto@apolloaisystems.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Apollo AI Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Redding</CityName>
<ZipCode>960010400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4087581593</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1267 Willis Street, STE 200</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
