<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: St. Louis Area Methods Meeting Graduate Student Colloquium - Ames, Iowa - April 20, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Saint Louis Area Methods Meeting (SLAMM) provides a unique opportunity for participants. It is large enough to attract high quality researchers, but small enough for individuals to get important feedback on their work and develop mentoring and professional networks. The graduate students funded by this project stand to benefit in both ways. First, the work that they present will get critical comments from leading methodologists and statisticians. In addition to the senior scholars presenting, several others will attend the conference as discussants. Theses senior scholars will include guests from other universities as well as members of the Department of Statistics at Iowa State University, which will encourage interdisciplinary work. Getting feedback on their research posters from these scholars will significantly improve the quality of their work. Second, the connections the graduate students make with the faculty have the potential to have long lasting effects. Students will be assigned a specific mentor and the individualized relationship will hopefully last beyond this meeting. These networking connections can have lasting effects on a person's scholarship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participation of the graduate students at SLAMM has clear implications for their educational success. Many of the students will be presenting dissertation related research and the feedback will improve their education experiences. In addition, the many of graduate students will be from underrepresented groups, which have traditionally not participated in these types of meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1820923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Peterson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>daveamp@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
<LastName>Chyzh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ochyzh@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Nieman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mdnieman@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
