<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: High Performance Low Power Dense Server for Cloud</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to accelerate the most common computations in processing Big Data and performing real-time analyses on data streaming-in to enterprise data centers. For the same total cost, the technology advanced by the proposed project is expected to increase performance by a factor of 12. As part of this improvement, it is expected to reduce the energy per instruction by a factor of 25 times or greater. This frees businesses to apply more advanced analytics techniques and react more quickly to changing business conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses the ever-growing need to process more data, but on a fixed budget. The objective is to provide accelerator technology for an increasingly critical set of applications that are currently underserved by generic CPU technology. The project aims eventually to deliver a PCIe accelerator card populated by silicon chips based on a new type of accelerator micro-architecture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1820507</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Halle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>seanhalle@intensivate.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Intensivate Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Fremont</CityName>
<ZipCode>945393680</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314408718</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>40087 Mission Blvd., Suite #274</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
