<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Parameterizing sub-grid Arctic snow-on-sea-ice processes in Earth System Models using MOSAiC field observations and realistic-resolution process models.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600571.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600571</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will help answer one of the key questions being asked by the international Arctic climate-science community: What is the role of snow-on-sea-ice in controlling heat exchanges in the Arctic climate system? This work will educate young scientists in the combined issues of field measurements, high-resolution modeling, and representing high-resolution processes in regional and global models. In addition, it will collect high quality field measurements that will advance Arctic system science for years to come.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This research will synthesize three interrelated science contributions: (1) Multidisciplinary drifting Observatory for the Study of Arctic Climate (MOSAiC) field observations will identify governing physical processes, fluxes, and linkages within the Arctic climate system. (2) Realistic-resolution (meters-scale), physically based modeling tools (e.g., MicroMet, SnowModel, EnBal, SnowPack, SnowTran-3D, SnowDunes, SnowAssim, SeaIce-3D) will quantify the behavior, interactions, and sensitivities among the Arctic system components. (3) Field observations and high-resolution modeling will be integrated to define what is missing or poorly represented in Earth System Models and guide the parameterization of the associated snow-related processes and fluxes for the Community Earth System Model (CESM) and the Los Alamos Sea Ice Model (CICE).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1820927</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glen</FirstName>
<LastName>Liston</LastName>
<EmailAddress>glen.liston@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>072Z</Code>
<Text>NNA-Navigating the New Arctic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
