<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Increasing the Visibility of Women's Research in Mathematics through Graduate Student Participation in National Workshops</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49966.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49966</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the participation of graduate students in workshops presented by the Association for Women in Mathematics at four major U.S. mathematics meetings in 2018-2020: SIAM 2018 (July, Portland), JMM 2019 (January, Baltimore), SIAM CSE 2019 (February, Spokane), and JMM 2020 (January, Denver). These workshops will bring rising women stars and current mathematical leaders together with graduate students and recent graduates from a variety of fields in pure and applied mathematics. By creating a rich intellectual community centered on shared research interests, the events are structured to generate new mentoring relations, new research collaborations, and increased activity in the associated research areas.  Moreover, these events at highly visible national meetings benefit the entire mathematical community by showcasing the excellent mathematical work done by women.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Each workshop has a particular research focus.  Leaders in each research field will introduce younger mathematicians to a deeper understanding of the field and its connections with their own work.  Graduate students will, in turn, share their research during poster sessions and small group interactions.  The research topics to be highlighted in these workshops include modeling boundaries of objects in two and three dimensions, computational topology, and other topics that span a broad spectrum of current mathematical problems. The workshops aim to promote the research of young women mathematicians and to increase the visibility of research done by women mathematicians on questions of current interest. For more information on the workshops, see &lt;br/&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/awmmath/awm-at-siam and &lt;br/&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/awmmath/awm-at-jmm&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821955</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alejandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Alvarado</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aalvarado2@eiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ami</FirstName>
<LastName>Radunskaya</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aer04747@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karoline</FirstName>
<LastName>Pershell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>karoline.pershell@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association for Women in Mathematics, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029042213</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4014554086</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Charles St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
