<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2018 APS Intersociety Meeting - Comparative Physiology: Complexity and Integration Travel Award Program, New Orleans, Louisiana, October 25-28, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds travel expenses for undergraduate and graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and early career investigators, in particular individuals from underrepresented groups, who present research results at the American Physiological Society (APS) Intersociety Meeting, Comparative Physiology: Complexity and Integration, in New Orleans, Louisiana, October 25-28, 2018. The meeting will be a venue for the presentation of significant advances in understanding the integrative physiology of organisms, including humans and other animals. This meeting is an opportunity for comparative physiologists to report their newest research discoveries and to develop collaborations that spark scientific innovation. Broader impacts of the meeting include: significant advancement of knowledge about organismal physiology; greater participation of individuals from underrepresented groups in comparative physiology research; development of a globally diverse and more collaborative research workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2018 APS Intersociety Meeting, Comparative Physiology: Complexity and Integration, seeks to promote the exchange of ideas and development of future collaborations of comparative and evolutionary physiologists internationally, and to encourage trainees, early career investigators, and individuals from underrepresented groups to pursue research careers in this discipline. The conference includes plenary lectures, symposia, contributed oral and poster presentations, and workshops on career development and technological/educational advances. In order to achieve the conference objectives above, APS will administer a travel grant program offering travel awards to trainees (undergraduate/graduate students and postdoctoral fellows) and early career investigators, in particular individuals from underrepresented groups (women, racial/ethnic minorities, and disabled persons), who submit abstracts to be presented at the meeting. Travel awards resulting from this award will be directed to individuals working in the research areas supported by the NSF Division of Integrative Organismal Systems. The project will contribute to broadening the participation of young scientists, with an emphasis on members of under-represented groups, exposing them to cutting edge physiological research and providing unique opportunities for professional development and networking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821028</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Frank</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mfrank@the-aps.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/02/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dane</FirstName>
<LastName>Crossley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dane.crossley@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/02/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dane</FirstName>
<LastName>Crossley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dane.crossley@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/02/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Physiological Society</Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<ZipCode>208524911</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3016347168</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6120 Executive Blvd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
