<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning for the long-term impact of the Dordt College agriculture stewardship center on basic research and education related to ecological sustainability in the rural Midwest</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for planning the long-term impact of the Dordt College agriculture stewardship center (DC-ASC) on basic research and education related to ecological sustainability in the rural Midwest.  The center is strategically located in the heart of some of the most highly productive and valued agricultural land and livestock production in the nation. The center is undergoing major change with land acquisition, building changes, and the construction of a new $4.8 million teaching and outreach center.  There is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity to direct and substantially increase the long-term development and impact of the DC-ASC on basic research and education related to ecological sustainability in the rural Midwest that will serve needs of the 4-state region of Iowa, Minnesota, South Dakota, and Nebraska.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will bring together regional area leaders in agriculture, education, governments of states and municipalities, university extension, and businesses to develop a strategic plan for long-term direction and development of the DC-ASC to best serve the needs of the region in a responsible and sustainable manner.  The project will address regional ecological issues, future education endeavors, direction for future research of high priority in the region and will provide direction for future infrastructure development of the DC-ASC as a regional service center in service to the needs developed in the planning process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821110</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
<LastName>Ploegstra</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeff.ploegstra@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Duane</FirstName>
<LastName>Bajema</LastName>
<EmailAddress>duane.bajema@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>DeHaan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>robert.dehaan@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hummel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeremy.hummel@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>DeVries</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gary.devries@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dordt College</Name>
<CityName>Sioux Center</CityName>
<ZipCode>512501606</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7127226264</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>498 4th Avenue NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>085Y</Code>
<Text>ICB: Infrastructure Capacity f</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
