<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improving Ocean Access for Research and Teaching at the Gulf of Maine Research Institute</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>95561</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The intense annual cycle and strong tides make the Gulf of Maine ecosystem incredibly productive, and it supports a high biomass of fish, whales, and seabirds. This ecosystem has historically been home to highly productive fisheries, including the fishery for Atlantic cod that was critical to the founding of the nation. This ecosystem is now warming at four times the global average rate, and this warming combined with generations of overfishing has led to the collapse of the region's iconic cod fishery. The Gulf of Maine Research Institute (GMRI) is the only institution dedicated to understanding the Gulf of Maine ecosystem. Scientists at GMRI conduct integrated, interdisciplinary research across the food web, from plankton to people. Beginning in 2019, this team will include students participating in a new NSF REU program. Much of GMRI's field research involves collecting fish ranging in size from juvenile alewife a few centimeters long to 2 meter-long bluefin tuna. These standard-sized chest freezers are now scattered throughout the building, creating an inefficient use of space and energy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While GMRI is located on the waterfront in Portland, ME, the institute does not have direct access to the water. Furthermore, as the pace of sampling has increased, GMRI has had to add additional capacity to store frozen specimens. This project will fund the construction of a 12'-by-24' floating dock to provide safe access to the water for scientists, students, and marine educators. It will also fund acquisition of a large (8'-by-20') walk-in freezer to provide efficient storage of frozen specimens for research and teaching. The two projects supported by this funding were identified as part of a comprehensive strategic plan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821061</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Pershing</LastName>
<EmailAddress>apershing@gmri.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/19/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gulf of Maine Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>041010000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2077722321</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>350 Commericial Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>085Y</Code>
<Text>ICB: Infrastructure Capacity f</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
