<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Workshop on the Economics of Cloud Computing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>90593</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Public cloud computing is rapidly becoming the foundation of our information-based economy. Users are&lt;br/&gt;adopting cloud platforms in lieu of maintaining dedicated computing infrastructure primarily due to the&lt;br/&gt;resulting savings in costs. Since cloud platforms earn revenue from utilizing their infrastructure by&lt;br/&gt;renting it out to customers, and earn no revenue if their infrastructure is idle, their goal is to maximize&lt;br/&gt;utilization. The increasing complexity of cloud markets raises new research&lt;br/&gt;challenges for both users and providers that are inherently economic. This award will support the&lt;br/&gt;organization of a workshop to bring together researchers from computer systems and networks and from&lt;br/&gt;the fields of economics, finance, and operations research to define important research challenges at the&lt;br/&gt;intersection of economics and cloud computing over the next 5-10 years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research agenda of the workshop has the potential for broad and transformative impact on the US and&lt;br/&gt;beyond by fostering a new interdisciplinary community in this nascent area, identifying its key research&lt;br/&gt;challenges, and laying the foundation for future innovations that increase the efficiency of using cloud&lt;br/&gt;computing resources. Furthermore, the workshop will engage early career scholars and those from&lt;br/&gt;diverse backgrounds and underrepresented groups to connect them with a broad community of academic&lt;br/&gt;and industrial researchers interested in the intersection of economics and computer systems and&lt;br/&gt;networking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821682</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Irwin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>irwin@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>Computer Systems Research (CSR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
