<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symposium on Motor Control in Biomechanics 2018, May 29 2018; Minneapolis (USA)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>14074</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the 2018 Motor Control in Biomechanics Symposium, which will be held on May 29, 2018, in advance of the American College of Sports Medicine meeting in Minneapolis, MN.  This symposium will bring together researchers to discuss new tools and approaches of motor control and biomechanics that can be applied to advance research in sports medicine.  The theme of the symposium is "Innovative Techniques towards a New Approach to Sports and Exercise."  The symposium will be structured to allow experts in the field of biomechanics and motor control to present the leading edge of research to a broad audience that includes not only engineers but also more clinical researchers in sports medicine and exercise science.  The research that will be discussed, and the integration of biomechanics and motor control, is also directly relevant to studies of pathological motion and rehabilitation for individuals who have sustained an or who have a disability.  Award funds will support travel grants for young investigators and junior faculty to allow them to attend an additional day of the overall conference, as well as partial travel funds for some of the invited speakers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This symposium will focus on cutting edge research technologies that have been developed in the areas of motion control and biomechanics and how they can be applied to translational research.  Key to the success of this symposium will be the fact that it brings together convergent groups of researchers from engineering, clinical medicine, physical therapy, and exercise science to discuss the latest advances and how different disciplines can work together to address current research questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1821895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamill</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jhamill@kin.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
