<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Uncertainty and Youth Well-being</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Toby Parcel</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This study expands scientific understanding of how an increase in uncertainty affects youth well-being. In a community in which some youth experience uncertainty and others do not, there is an opportunity to analyze whether, how, and to what extent changes in uncertainty affect youth. The findings from this study will inform discussions at the federal, state, and local levels about ways to increase well-being among youth, who face varying levels of uncertainty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will use multiple waves of representative California statewide data collected via the California Health Interview Survey from 2007-2016 (n=238,000), with subsequent years added as they are released. The project will estimate the impact of uncertainty by comparing youth who are and are not subject to uncertainty. It will follow both groups of youth longitudinally. Study outcomes include employment status, educational enrollment and attainment, and various measures of physical and psychological well-being. In addition, the project will examine spillover effects to the broader community. To further analyze findings, the project will produce an original longitudinal survey and in-depth interview study of 502 young people from the community in California. The project will compare key outcomes of these youth over the period between 2014 and 2020, thus allowing causal inferences regarding the impact of earlier events on later outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1822787</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>erhamilton@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caitlin</FirstName>
<LastName>Patler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>patler@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
