<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Meeting: 2018 Institute on Teaching and Learning, Physiology Educator's Community of Practice Fellowships</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen Carpenter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Science educators benefit from ongoing professional development to learn about and implement evidence-based practices in teaching, learning, and assessment in their classrooms.  To this end, the American Physiological Society convenes a biennial Institute on Teaching and Learning to provide postsecondary educators an opportunity to share education research and best practices relating to improving science teaching and learning.  This year's institute will be held June 18-22, 2018 in Madison, Wisconsin. This project will support twenty physiology educators to attend the Institute and to participate in a year-long immersion in the Physiology Educators Community of Practice, which engages in online professional development activities including discussion groups and online courses about the scholarship of teaching and learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fellowships will support the participation of trainees (graduate students and postdocs), early career educators, community college faculty, and faculty from underrepresented groups or minority-serving institutions in the 2018 Institute of Teaching and Learning.  The Institute will address topics such as best practices in teaching, scholarship of teaching and learning, integrating research into undergraduate classrooms, and assessment of activities.  More than half of the planned institute speakers are female, and more than 10% are members of underrepresented groups.  Candidates for the fellowship will be current members of the American Physiological Society (APA), who submit an abstract for the meeting and a fellowship application.  An organizing committee, comprised of faculty from different institutional types and representatives of the APA, will review applications and select fellowship recipients.  Fellows will be expected to attend the 2018 Institute of Teaching and Learning and to participate in professional development activities throughout the subsequent year.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1822245</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marsha</FirstName>
<LastName>Matyas</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mmatyas@the-aps.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Goodman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bgoodman@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Goodman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bgoodman@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Physiological Society</Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<ZipCode>208524911</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3016347168</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6120 Executive Blvd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
