<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on Graph Decompositions at Michigan Technological University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funds to support expenses for participants of the 4th Annual Kliakhandler Conference on Graph Decompositions, which will be held on August 9-11, 2018 on the campus of Michigan Technological University. The purpose of this conference is to stimulate research activity and collaboration between members of the mathematical sciences community. The conference is focused in the area of graph decompositions. Graph decomposition problems regularly appear in the fields of graph theory, design theory, and algebra and have applications to  communication, optimization, and algorithms.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will also include a special session titled "Everyday Combinatorics", which will focus on combinatorics at the high school level.  A combinatorics specialist with an interest in math education will organize the session, and local high school teachers will be invited to attend. The website address for the conference is http://kliak.mtu.edu/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1822277</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
