<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on Combinatorics and its Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Conference on Combinatorics and its Applications is a three day event to be held at the new Novena Campus of Nanyang Technological University (NTU), Singapore, from 14 to 16 July 2018.  Combinatorial design theory lies at the crossroads of combinatorics, algebra, geometry, number theory, and mathematics of computation. It has extensive applications in communications, cryptography and security, experimental design, networking, coding theory, software testing, and bioinformatics, to list a few. The conference includes keynote presentations from nine renowned experts from Asia, Europe, North America and Australia, whose research spans these topics.  The conference has strong international participation and thus affords many opportunities for collaboration among researchers and educators in combinatorics and its applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference is supported by Nanyang Technological University (NTU), the Institute of Advanced Studies at NTU, The Institute of Combinatorics and its Applications (ICA), and the U.S. National Science Foundation (NSF). Specifically, this NSF grant broadens the participation of U.S. researchers working at the intersection of combinatorial design theory and computer science, expanding and strengthening this community.  The participants will be selected through a travel grant application process, giving preference to women, minorities, under-represented groups, and beginning researchers. More information about the conference, and a description of the travel grant application process, may be found at the conference website: https://tinyurl.com/combinatorics-and-its-apps&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823290</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
