<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sociocultural Determinants of Human Motives</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>379337</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven J. Breckler</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding the basic human motives that drive behavior has been a question of great historical significance in psychology.  Yet, an integrative theory, allowing for different sociocultural and individual factors that might prioritize one kind of motive over another, is still missing.  This project aims to develop a theoretical model of the sociocultural determinants of human motives.  To develop a powerful testbed, with strong broader impacts, the research examines why and how individual actions are motivated in response to environmental challenges. Environmental crises such as pollution or the depletion of natural resources pose some of the greatest collective challenges faced by society today. Responses of individuals to these challenges have critical consequences. By understanding what drives people's actions in this context, progress will be made in addressing a fundamental question about human behavior. The research is expected to have wide impact across a number of scholarly disciplines, with important implications for public policy, education and philanthropy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theory proposes that different sociocultural and individual factors orient people towards more internal and personal reasons or toward more external and social reasons for their actions.  The factors that orient people toward more internal and personal reasons for their actions include individualistic values, high socioeconomic status, and social belonging.  The factors that orient people toward more external and social reasons for their actions include collectivistic values, low socioeconomic status, and social isolation.  The research examines the extent to which environmental beliefs versus perceived environmental norms drive pro-environmental behaviors, and how this differs for people from a wide range of personal experiences and backgrounds. The explanatory role of sense of control and attention allocation is also investigated. The studies use diverse methodologies including a nationally representative study of Americans, a laboratory behavioral study, a longitudinal study of daily environmental behaviors, and a community field experiment at local grocery stores assessing shopping behavior. The new theoretical model can also be used to understand why and how individual actions are motivated in response to a broad range of collective challenges, including widespread infectious disease and the threat of terrorism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heejung</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>heejung.kim@psych.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Sherman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>david.sherman@psych.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
