<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interdisciplinary Postdoctoral Fellowship in Behavioral and Forensic Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>237648.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>119359</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>reginald sheehan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Interdisciplinary Postdoctoral Fellowship in Behavioral and Forensic Sciences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support an interdisciplinary postdoctoral fellow who will conduct research under the mentorship of senior scholars in the fields of behavior sciences and forensic sciences at Arizona State University. The past decade has seen the beginning of a major transformation in the field of forensic science. This postdoctoral fellow's research program will advance scientific understanding at the nexus of the behavioral sciences and forensic sciences, with a goal to improve how forensic science is developed, conducted, and communicated. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support a postdoctoral scholar who will be engaged in a number of research areas at Arizona State University?s Forensic Science Initiative Program and Law and Behavioral Science Program for two years. The research will involve developing ways to test the validity and reliability of forensic techniques, investigating the human side of forensic judgment, and helping non-scientists such as jurors, lawyers, and judges understand and evaluate the quality of forensic science by improving how it is communicated. The postdoctoral fellow will receive consistent and ongoing mentorship from a team of scholars with established research records in the area of the fellow?s work. The goal of this interdisciplinary postdoctoral fellowship is to facilitate the growth of a scholar working in a critically-understudied area at the intersection of the behavioral and forensic sciences, in order to advance scientific understandings of convergence of these important areas of study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823741</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Saks</LastName>
<EmailAddress>saks@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gwyneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Gordon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Gwyneth.Gordon@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Schweitzer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>njs@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Salerno</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jessica.salerno@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Falsetti</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Anthony.Falsetti@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/26/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
