<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Postdoctoral Fellowship in Law and Health</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>215348</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Bornstein</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Postdoctoral Fellowship in Law and Health&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support a postdoctoral fellow who will conduct research under the mentorship of senior scholars of law, gender, and health at the University of Michigan. Concerted field-building efforts over the last few years have resulted in a promising set of theoretical tools and methods for approaching the scientific study of relationships between law and health. The postdoctoral fellow's research program will advance scientific understandings by bringing theoretical depth to the study of the intersections of law and health.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will nurture a post-doctoral scholar to be housed at the Institute for Research on Women and Gender at the University of Michigan. The postdoctoral fellow will spend two years at the University of Michigan performing research in gender, law, and health using interdisciplinary methods such as interviewing, statistical analysis, and participant observation. The postdoctoral fellow will receive consistent and ongoing mentorship from a team of scholars with established research records in the area of the fellow's work. The goals of the project are for the postdoctoral fellow to advance an excellent research agenda, to publish articles on law and health in peer reviewed journals, to hone grant writing skills, to establish relationships nationally with scholars in the field, and to envision and execute a long-term vision of the fellow's research trajectory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823629</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirkland</LastName>
<EmailAddress>akirklan@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Levitsky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>slevitsk@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
