<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Embedded Machine Vision for Accurate Gait Analyses and Body Movement Measurements</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to revolutionize conventional rehabilitation assistant and body movement assessment tools with low-cost machine vision based solutions by maximizing the capability of ubiquitous tablets and 2D cameras, which have significant cost and accessibility advantage over more expensive 3D cameras. A set of tablet/smartphone Apps can be developed base on the embedded machine vision technology, and the team plan to create related services using a subscription model. This innovation will benefit broad healthcare market, which includes rehab facilities, surgery/neurology outpatient clinics, physical therapy clinics, stroke centers, and individuals. Overall, the innovation will make embedded machine vision technology accessible to and serve many population groups in the society. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on preliminary results that we obtained on a PC platform to identify and track human body joint points in close to real-time. The prototype leverages novel machine learning algorithms and high performance processors (graphics processing units). Our next phase of research is to generate depth map from a 2D camera, recognize and track body joint points, and score body movements, all on a tablet platform. The challenges include depth generation with 2D images and efficient models and algorithms to execute on a resource constraint embedded platform. The team will leverage embedded deep learning techniques to optimize the algorithms towards an embedded processor architecture on modern tablets so that the proof-of-concept can deliver satisfactory performance. The team also plan to work with a medical doctor and a rehabilitation facility advisor to review and refine the software features and validate the early prototype.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823766</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
<LastName>Luo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Yan_Luo@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/07/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<ZipCode>018543643</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 Suffolk Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
