<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Influence of Legal Institutions on Legal Mobilization</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>18348</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Bornstein</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Influence of Legal Institutions on Legal Mobilization&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Legal institutions are integral to achieving social, economic, and political mobilization. The process of legal mobilization requires claimants to understand and perceive their legal rights and means of recourse. The project will assess citizens' understanding and perception of legal institutions and how such understanding influences their ability to engage in litigation to pursue their legal rights. The project will also evaluate the conditions under which citizens mobilize courts while it explores the conditions under which citizens express willingness to use courts to mobilize their claims.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project links the literatures on legal mobilization, judicial impact, and judicial interpretation under the theoretical rubric of law and society in order to engage in fieldwork to explore the conditions under which Black South Africans express willingness to use courts to mobilize their claims. By focusing on socio-economic rights, the project will focus on how these citizens interpret their constitutional rights and courts' ability to satisfy those rights, and how that interpretation affects their choice to use legal strategies. Interviews will be conducted with citizens who have employed the legal system to pursue their rights, to ascertain their perceptions of their legal institutions' ability to protect their constitutional rights. Findings will provide insight into citizens' perceptions of constitutional rights and of the influences of legal institutions on legal mobilization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1823644</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mccarthy@legal.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kira</FirstName>
<LastName>Tait</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ktait@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
