<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC* NPEO: The Research and Science Engagement Center: A Production Platform for Operations, Applied Training, Monitoring, and R&amp;E Support</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>1166667</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The scientific community has experienced an unprecedented shift in the way&lt;br/&gt;research is performed and how discoveries are made. Highly sophisticated experimental instruments are&lt;br/&gt;creating massive datasets for diverse scientific communities and hold the potential for new insights that&lt;br/&gt;will have long-lasting impacts on society. However, scientists cannot make effective use of this data if&lt;br/&gt;they are unable to move, store, and analyze it. This project establishes the Research and Science&lt;br/&gt;Engagement Center (ReSEC) as a collaborative focal point for operational expertise and analysis.&lt;br/&gt;This project will assist scientists in routinely, reliably, and robustly transferring their data.&lt;br/&gt;ReSEC will deliver end-to-end user support and network engineering solutions,&lt;br/&gt;and become a central community hub ready to provide personalized expertise and assistance on an ongoing basis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ReSEC proposes four primary execution thrusts: 1) a Roadside Assistance center to reactively&lt;br/&gt;respond to immediate problems with science data transfers; 2) proactive network observation&lt;br/&gt;using tools such as perfSONAR and NetSage; 3) assistance with design &amp; deployment of campus&lt;br/&gt;networking assets such as Science DMZs; and 4) training for campus network administrators.&lt;br/&gt;ReSEC will scale operations broadly by relying on Regional Network, Infrastructure and Science Community partners.&lt;br/&gt;ReSEC will deliver expertise and assistance on a sustainable, ongoing basis, with a particular emphasis&lt;br/&gt;on serving educational institutions with relatively limited local network administrative resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1826994</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Zurawski</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zurawski@es.net</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Schopf</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jmschopf@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Jent</LastName>
<EmailAddress>djent@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
