<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of Community Light Scattering Computational Capabilities</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>593862.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This study seeks to develop theoretical and computational methods to improve simulations of optical properties of non-spherical particles over a broad range of size parameters.  Applications of the theoretical/computational work span many broad areas of physics, chemistry, and engineering; with specific importance in atmospheric and oceanic sciences, combustion science, astrophysics, bio-optics, manufacturing diagnostics and control, and many other fields.  This study will train graduate students and post-doctoral scholars.  After testing and optimization, this research group plans to release the computational programs as open-source codes to the research community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study seeks to expand previous NSF-funded research to develop advanced capabilities based on the invariant imbedding T-matrix method (II-TM) for simulating the optical properties of non-spherical, inhomogeneous particles with small to moderate size parameters.  This study seeks to further improve the II-TM from both theoretical and numerical perspectives.  This group recently developed a preliminary version of a physical geometric optics model (PGOM) based on either an electromagnetic volume- or a surface-integral relation for large size parameters.  The suite of PGOM and II-TM will represent state-of-the-art light scattering computational capabilities, with a wide range of applications in atmospheric/oceanic radiative transfer and remote sensing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1826936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ping</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pyang@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Panetta</LastName>
<EmailAddress>r-panetta@geos.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
