<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Support for the 2018 Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium; Austin, Texas; August 13-15, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Schmid</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant provides support for 80 students to participate in the Twenty-Ninth Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication (SFF) Symposium, An Additive Manufacturing Conference to be held August 13-15, 2018, in Austin, Texas.  The SFF Symposium is widely considered one of the premier academic conference on additive manufacturing (AM) related research in the world.  In 2017, it brought together 654 researchers from universities, national laboratories, and companies from 20 countries around the world, who together presented 473 technical presentations and posters during the 3-day event. Students will have the opportunity to engage in 3 days of technical sessions focused on the latest advances in AM applications, process development, materials, modeling, and design. All student awardees will be expected to present a paper and/or poster during the symposium and to attend all 3 days of the event. The funding opportunity will be announced broadly and early enough to provide ample time for students to apply. Awardees will be selected by committee and the awards will cover the cost of student registration.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By attending and presenting their work in the symposium, students will gain extensive knowledge and understanding of the state of cutting-edge research in AM.  They will also have the opportunity for professional development by delivering a technical presentation to a highly knowledgeable audience.  Furthermore, they will have the opportunity to network with other professional and student researchers in the AM field and thereby build their personal network of future collaborators and colleagues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1826959</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Seepersad</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ccseepersad@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
