<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Physiological mechanisms affecting non-human primate mate choice</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In many mammals, male characteristics and behaviors may limit female mate choice.  Discrepancies between observed mate choice and actual paternity suggest, however, that females may exert influence over offspring paternity through physiological preference. This doctoral dissertation project will explore how genetics and physiology influence primate mate choice, generating novel data on primate reproductive physiology. The project also will provide mentorship and training in field, laboratory, bioinformatics and statistical methods for students from groups under-represented in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will explore physiological mechanisms by which olive baboons may exert post-breeding mate choice. The co-PI will collect reproductive physiological data for both males and females. Social behaviors will also be recorded to investigate the concordance between pre- and post-breeding choice. This study will improve understanding of post-breeding mechanisms of choice in primates and inform the broader primate comparative context for understanding the unique suite of reproductive and morphological characteristics seen in humans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1826804</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Higham</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jhigham@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Petersen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rp2276@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
