<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a gamma-ray spectrometer for surface-process and ocean research</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>118947.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>118947</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Russell Kelz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Maintenance of soil is critically important for sustaining the world's growing population.  Eroded surface sediment can also be a major pollutant degrading aquatic ecosystems worldwide through light attenuation and heavy-metal contamination.  This instrumentation grant will add to sediment mobility research through the measurement of decay products from naturally produced radioactive isotopes adsorbed to sediment. This instrument will help build a foundation for efforts to (1) create new datasets, (2) enhance infrastructure for interdisciplinary, collaborative research, and (3) train a diverse workforce capable of tackling society's environmental challenges through student training. Education impacts of this grant include the incorporation of the instrument into a new course and undergraduate student research projects through the NSF-funded Research Experience for Undergraduates program at Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UC San Diego. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Measurement of fallout radionuclides provide a means to measure rates of surficial processes. Specifically, the short-lived beryllium nuclide 7Be can be used to understand the chemically similar 10Be radionuclide commonly used in surface-process research but typically only measured by more expensive accelerator mass spectrometry.  Detection of the abundant short-lived beryllium radionuclide (7Be) via acquisition of a Canberra/Mirion U-Style Cryostat Small Anode Germanium (SAGe) Well Detector System will facilitate research into the mobility of cosmogenic 10Be and the adsorption behavior of 9Be, which is a toxic pollutant. The acquisition of this instrument will drive scientific research (some already NSF-funded) and innovation and cultivate interdisciplinary collaborations among researchers studying low-temperature geochemistry, marine geoscience, ecology, archaeology, and Earth-surface dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1828314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
<LastName>Willenbring</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jwillenbring@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
