<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Management of West Coast Winch Pool 2018-2022</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3259184.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Funding is requested for Scripps Institution of Oceanography who maintains the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS) West Coast Winch Pool for the benefit of U.S. ocean scientists.  The winch pool is a shared-use facility that procures, maintains, upgrades, and makes available a variety of portable oceanographic winches that are used by scientists aboard a broad range of research vessels.  The pool currently includes a deep-sea traction winch, three light-duty winches, four general purpose mooring spoolers, one large mooring spooler, a double-barrel capstan, and a tensioning wire spooling system.  Winches are shared following community-based scheduling methods run by UNOLS. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under Merit Review Criterion 2 of the Proposal Guidelines (NSF 13-589). It provides infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1828945</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Appelgate</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bappelgate@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelety</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zkelety@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5416</Code>
<Text>SHIPBOARD SCIENTIFIC SUPP EQUI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
