<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a Modern Capillary Genetic Analyzer for Multi-investigator Research in Population, Phylogeographic, Phylogenetic, and Behavioral Genetics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>71004</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to the University of Tampa (UT) for acquisition of a capillary electrophoresis instrument, the SeqStudioTM, for separation and study of nucleic acids (DNA). It will greatly facilitate a variety of behavioral, ecological, population genetic, environmental, and evolution research projects and research-training of undergraduate students. This instrument will replace an earlier generation labor-intensive single capillary instrument, and permit quick adoption by numerous faculty at UT.  UT is primarily an undergraduate institution and currently engaged in a campus-wide initiative which provides funding assistance to faculty to convert courses to include student inquiry. The biology department has long been dedicated to maintaining high levels of involvement by undergraduates in faculty research. Graduating senior exit surveys indicate that 60% to 95% of graduating students have been involved in research outside the classroom. Thus it is not surprising that 40-50% of graduating seniors indicate that they wish to continue in graduate or professional programs in STEM fields. Undergraduates majoring in biology are nearly 75% female; 22% are members of underrepresented ethnic or racial minorities; and 14% are first generation college students. These ratios are reflected in the investigators' research laboratories, and funding assistance exists to further encourage underrepresented students to participate in research. Further, all of the investigators carry out research that emphasizes environmental science and that informs conservation decision-making. Therefore, acquisition of the SeqStudioTM will expose the next the generation of scientists to cutting-edge research and instrumentation and increase STEM as well as environmental competencies and our global competiveness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SeqStudioTM Genetic Analyzer is a four capillary electrophoresis instrument for separating and visualizing DNA bases and fragments. Each of the six investigators carry out research on wild organisms, the focus of which spans questions that can be answered using DNA techniques from the behavioral level, to the population level, to the phylogeographic, to the species delineation and identification level, and even to the deep phylogenetic level. Studies include conservation, ecological and evolutionary genetic studies on a variety of wild animal species, characterizing the retinal opsin genes and expressed proteins from marine vertebrate, the evolution and diversification of male parental care in fishes, the reproductive behavior of fish, and the ecology and distribution of seahorses and pipefishes in Tampa Bay, the Florida Keys and the Bahamas. The SeqStudioTM has the capability of running DNA sequences, fragment analysis (genotyping), and SNP genotyping, and will permit expanded capabilities for research labs on campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1828101</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
<LastName>Masonjones</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hmasonjones@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffry</FirstName>
<LastName>Fasick</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jfasick@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristine</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<EmailAddress>knwhite@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalia</FirstName>
<LastName>Belfiore</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nbelfiore@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Middlebrooks</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mmiddlebrooks@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tampa</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336061450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8132573889</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>401 W Kennedy Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
