<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI Acquisition: A Reconfigurable Computing Infrastructure Enabling Interdisciplinary and Collaborative Research in Hampton Roads</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1504396.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1504396</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rita Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project acquires a reconfigurable computing system that wiil support a broad spectrum of research projects in an appropriately tailored computer environment using state-of the-art technologies. It offers substantial computational power to support a number of critical research initiatives at the institution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This infrastructure, named DISCOVER, enables big data and high-performance computing research. Three key thrusts are emphasized: Cybersecurity, Resilience, and Data Intensive Science and Engineering. Each thrust includes multiple applications, as follows. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cybersecurity: hardware security for cryptographic circuit verification; modeling learning with homomorphic encryption; malware and anomaly detection; and modeling cyber-attack paths and their mitigation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Resilience: computational simulations to model sea level rise; understanding social media for emergency preparedness for natural disasters; and data-driven understanding of massive geospatial traffic patterns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data Intensive Science and Engineering: high-accuracy finite element mesh generation; analysis of brain imaging and image-guided surgery; and modelling of power-consumption and resource allocation for high-performance computing clusters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquired computing system will stimulate multi-disciplinary collaborations with other institutions in Hampton Roads, including Norfolk State University, Tidewater Community College, and Thomas Nelson Community College.  Training workshops and a summer institute will be organized to help students in various research fields to gain high-performance computing skills.  The insitution will leverage the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE) framework to address cyber workforce needs by increasing the pipeline of students pursuing cybersecurity careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1828593</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikos</FirstName>
<LastName>Chrisochoides</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nikos@cs.odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Masha</FirstName>
<LastName>Sosonkina</LastName>
<EmailAddress>msosonki@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>h1wu@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>j2huang@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Khan</FirstName>
<LastName>Iftekharuddin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kiftekha@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
