<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a Laser Scanning Confocal Microscope for Research and Teaching</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>396971</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to Loyola University Chicago (LUC) to support the acquisition of a laser-scanning confocal microscope. The acquisition of the proposed microscope will allow faculty to train students in the use of current technology in the context of independent research and academic instruction, as well as to advance their research programs. The Co-PIs on this grant mentor multiple undergraduates each year, providing students the opportunity to gain valuable research experience, to contribute to publications, and to present work at regional and national conferences. Undergraduate students will also utilize the confocal microscope in a Biological Imaging course, Cell Biology lab, and Course-Based Undergraduate Research Experiences, reaching more than 200 students each year. In addition, use of this microscope will be incorporated into multiple outreach programs, including two for high school students: the Emerging Biologists Workshop, an intensive one-week research experience, and the Biology Internship Program, an eight week internship. Finally, a collaboration with Ripon College has been established as part of an effort to share this technology with institutions that do not currently have it available. These programs demonstrate the commitment of LUC to engaging students in cutting-edge research, and exposing students to current technologies in the classroom and through community outreach. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A laser-scanning confocal microscope is absolutely essential to the research programs of numerous LUC faculty members spanning the Biology, Chemistry, and Psychology departments. Current laser-scanning confocal systems allow for the acquisition of data with increased resolution and speed, as well as reduced damage to samples over time. These advances allow for improved live imaging and the visualization of details at a cellular level that are critical for advancing our understanding of how tissues develop and function. Acquisition of this instrument will enhance research in the areas of gonad, craniofacial, and nervous system development, circadian rhythms, axon guidance, and drug addiction. This instrument will allow faculty to pursue cutting-edge research aims, and will contribute to the University's efforts to attract world-class researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1828164</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rodney</FirstName>
<LastName>Dale</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rdale1@luc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Rochlin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wrochli@luc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephan</FirstName>
<LastName>Steidl</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ssteidl@luc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Mierisch</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jmierisch@luc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cavanaugh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dcavanaugh1@luc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Loyola University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606601537</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7735082471</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1032 W. Sheridan Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
