<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2018 Solid State Chemistry Gordon Research Conference: Designing, Discovering, and Understanding the Functional Materials of the Future</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>26340</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2018 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) entitled Designing, Discovering, and Understanding the Functional Materials of the Future, is funded in-part by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program. It will be held at Colby-Sawyer College in New London, New Hampshire, beginning with the GRS on July 21-22, immediately followed by the GRC which runs from July 21-27, 2018.  The inclusive, collegial atmosphere of the GRC, and the emphasis on sharing previously unpublished information, enables the cultivation of innovative approaches to address the most important challenges facing our world. By including a mixture of students, postdocs, early career investigators, and distinguished veteran scientists the meeting will explore exciting new directions in the field, leverage the expertise of those with decades of experience, and inspire and educate future leaders. The meeting is structured to promote the exchange of ideas and the building of partnerships between researchers from academics, industry, and government laboratories. The GRS, which is a meeting solely for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, will promote an environment to introduce new graduate students into a conference atmosphere, allow all students and fellows to present their work in a low stress environment, and promote networking among peers.  The organizers are committed to a meeting that promotes diversity, with particular attention placed on encouraging participation of women, underrepresented minorities, and people with disabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Solid state chemistry plays a key role in the design, discovery, and optimization of new functional materials to meet ever-growing societal demands for smaller, faster, cleaner, and more sustainable technologies.  The Gordon Research Conference on Solid State Chemistry is a unique meeting that brings together a diverse group of scientists investigating solid state materials and their applications. This conference will provide perspectives from industry, national laboratories, and universities throughout the world on the most promising research directions in solid state and materials chemistry. An emphasis will be placed on exploring the synergies between computations and theory, synthesis, and advanced characterization methods to discover and develop the materials of the future. Applications of these materials span many fields including energy conversion and storage, electronics, and quantum computing, among others. Speakers and poster presenters are explicitly encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished results, and new ideas. The organizers strongly encourage active contribution to discussions and participation in poster sessions, which offer an excellent opportunity for presenting and learning about new and exciting research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1829169</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodward</LastName>
<EmailAddress>woodward.55@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
