<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PARTIAL SUPPORT OF THE CONDENSED MATTER AND MATERIAL RESEARCH COMMITTEE</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>70000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This project provides one-year partial support for the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine's ("National Academies") Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC). CMMRC's impact goes beyond the confines of the condensed matter and materials research communities. First, these activities engage a group of leading scientists from across the subfields of condensed matter and materials science in joint deliberations and provide a learning environment for that body regarding the public-policy process for science and the position of those fields in the broader context of the physical sciences. Second, CMMRC activities lead to an improved understanding of condensed matter and materials science by the broader scientific and policy-making communities. By holding focused sessions and initiating studies, CMMRC will continue to educate researchers, policy makers, and the general public about advances in condensed matter and materials science and their beneficial impact in other fields of science and technology and for society, in general.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This project provides one-year partial support for the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine"s ("National Academies") Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC). The CMMRC consists of members drawn from universities, industry, and government laboratories, with expertise intended to cover the breadth of the condensed matter and materials research fields. The overarching guidelines of CMMRC include the following objectives: (1) to respond to requests for technical information and assistance, both from within the National Academies and from outside federal research agencies; (2) to initiate and oversee ad hoc studies in these fields and their multidisciplinary connections to other fields of science and technology; (3) to serve as long-term stewards for studies initiated under CMMRC's direction; (4) to act as an educational resource for the condensed matter and materials research communities and the agencies that support them; and (5) to provide a forum for discussion among condensed matter and materials scientists and Washington D.C. policymakers. To carry out those objectives, CMMRC meets on a semi-annual basis and between those meetings, conducts its business through telephone conferences.  During the one-year period covered by this proposal, CMMRC will devote time to working with sponsors in developing a set of appropriate activities for proposal for the next 3-year renewal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1830008</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
