<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2018 ACM SIGMETRICS International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems (SIGMETRICS 2018)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samee Khan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2018 Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) Special Interest Group on Measurement and Evaluation (SIGMETRICS) conference will be held at Beckman Center, Irvine, California on June 18-22, 2018. SIGMETRICS brings together professionals from academic and industrial backgrounds in what has become a premier forum for discussing the development and application of state-of-the-art, broadly applicable analytic, simulation, and measurement-based performance evaluation techniques. The SIGMETRICS conference presents innovative, exciting work related to all aspects of performance for all types of computer systems. Highly original ideas, new approaches, and/or ground breaking results are expected. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Travel support will make possible the participation of students who would otherwise be unable to attend. Particular attention is paid to directing support towards under-represented groups, e.g., gender or ethnic minorities and students from smaller or less well-known institutions. The support will provide students who attend with the opportunity to interact with a diverse group of mentors and peers, furthering their education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1830133</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlee</FirstName>
<LastName>Joe-Wong</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cjoewong@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>Computer Systems Research (CSR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
