<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: The Third TMS Summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals, and Materials Professions</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>29160</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is well recognized that a diverse workforce can lead to gains in productivity, competitiveness, and creativity. However, the rich diversity of the full U.S. population is often underutilized among the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) professions. To address this issue, The Minerals, Metals &amp; Materials Society (TMS) is organizing a follow-up event to its previous two summits on diversity and inclusion. The third TMS summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals, and Materials Professions (DMMM3) will take place on the campus of the University of California, Santa Barbara from July 23-24, 2018. While previous summits opened the conversation and identified the challenges to a more diverse and inclusive professional community, DMMM3 will focus on establishing a clear path to meaningful engagement and tangible action.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The third TMS summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals, and Materials Professions will primarily focus on three themes: (1) Engaging participants on the most recent social-science findings in the areas of diversity and inclusion while exploring current issues and potential solutions; (2) Measuring progress and ensuring positive outcomes for all through the establishment of well-informed and proactive measures and metrics; and (3) Transforming the professional community by implementing changes in workplace cultures and policies. To help equip attendees with their own toolbox of knowledge and skills to address diversity and inclusion in their workplace, the summit will include interactive discussions, panels, and several opportunities for professional development. The audience will include nearly 150 attendees who will have the opportunity to hear from more than 30 invited speakers from across industry, academia, and government.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1831733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jscott@tms.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Minerals Metals &amp; Materials Society</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152375851</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7248143178</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5700 Corporate Drive, 750</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
