<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Property-Ownership Implications for Resource Management in Critical Conservation Landscapes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>jacqueline vadjunec</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will analyze patterns of private land ownership in the Greater Yellowstone and Northern Great Plains regions to enhance understanding of how land acquisition and management by individuals with high-net worth affects natural resource management in rural, high-amenity regions of the western U.S. and other locales.  The researchers will quantify rates and volumes of land ownership change and will analyze landowner decision making about resource management and conservation at the property and landscape scales.  Project findings will assist in the development of an overarching model of the lifecycle of property ownership by individuals with high net worth.  Special foci of the project are the processes through which land-ownership change influences the success of cooperative wildlife management efforts.  By addressing knowledge gaps regarding emerging property-ownership regimes in rural landscapes, this research will help address issues related to the different perspectives of high net-worth, often-absent landowners and longer-term residents of high-amenity regions.  Through ongoing engagement with local and regional stakeholders in the design, execution, and dissemination stages of the project, the investigators will provide new information and insights that can address local issues and increase public scientific literacy and public engagement with science in rural America.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite increases in the number of individuals with high net worth as proprietors of natural resources worldwide, few scholars have examined the trajectories of these property ownership trends and their implications for resource-management institutions that act as mediators in social-ecological systems.  The investigators will quantify rates and patterns of ownership change through analyses of parcel and property sales data and qualitative key informant data.  They will employ ethnographic observation and in-depth interviews to characterize landowner resource-management decisions with a focus on key social and ecological influences, and they will analyze cooperative elk-management institutions using social network and institutional history approaches.  The investigators will use a recently developed property-landscape life course framework that focuses attention on spatial and temporal dynamics of the relationships linking private landowners, the resources they manage, and local institutions of resource management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1832452</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Gosnell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gosnellh@geo.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Haggerty</LastName>
<EmailAddress>julia.haggerty@montana.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montana State University</Name>
<CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9186</Code>
<Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
