<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel to the 2018 Annual Meeting of The Clay Minerals Society: Champaign, IL - June 9-14, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support 15 students from universities in the United States to attend the 55th Annual Meeting of The Clay Minerals Society at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign during June 8th-June 14th, 2018. The travel grants will target graduate students who will benefit from attending this conference, including the workshop on Medicinal Applications of Clay Minerals and field trips. Priority will be given to first-time attendees, and students from under-represented groups (female, minorities and students with disabilities).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The annual Clay Mineral Society conference is a premier international conference in clay science, held annually.  The conference will attract participants from many different scientific disciplines, from agriculture to materials science and engineering, and from many different countries. The program generally consists of a workshop and four-day technical sessions. Each technical session starts with an Award Lecture that will be followed by thematic sessions, which cover a broad range of clay sciences: clay mineralogy, crystallography, petrology, material science, nanoscience, medical and medicinal clay, environmental engineering, soil science, biogeochemistry, industrial technology, isotope geochemistry, cosmogeochemistry, advanced spectroscopies, and education. It is a unique opportunity for graduate students to participate and interact with international colleagues and leading researchers. The interaction during and post technical sessions will further enhance the research and education in clay sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1832389</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuji</FirstName>
<LastName>Arai</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yarai@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>GEOBIOLOGY &amp; LOW TEMP GEOCHEM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
