<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NYC Regional Math Alliance Conference at Kean University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8941.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8941</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for a one-day conference, The NYC Regional Math Alliance Conference, to be held at Kean University in New Jersey on September 15, 2018. The NYC Regional Math Alliance is an affiliate of the National Alliance for Doctoral Studies in the Mathematical Sciences (Math Alliance) that is focused on an effort to increase the number of students from underrepresented groups who obtain doctoral degrees in the mathematical sciences. The conference will highlight the research of students being mentored by the NYC Regional Math Alliance and will promote a continued interest in mathematics by fostering an atmosphere conducive to mathematical discussion and to the formulation and nurturing of new collaborations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will further the goal of increasing the numbers of students from underrepresented groups obtaining doctoral degrees in the mathematical sciences in several ways. On the one hand, the exposure of student participants to poster presentations and talks on mathematical research by their peers will heighten their interest in the subject. Meeting and interacting with faculty from PhD programs at nearby institutions presents the pursuit of a PhD as an accessible and realizable goal. Additionally, the conference will contribute to the building of a community of faculty interested in mentoring students from underrepresented groups. There are already a large number of faculty in the New Jersey and NYC area committed to the aims of the conference and this meeting will help organize and further their efforts. More details on the conference can be found on the webpage, http://mathalliance.ccny.cuny.edu/conference-2018/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1832866</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
