<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NISS Writing Workshop for New Researchers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Support for this conference provides partial participant support for the 2018 NISS Writing Workshop for Junior Researchers held at the Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM) July 29 and 31, 2018 in Vancouver, BC, Canada.  These funds support a technical writing workshop for 24 junior researchers in statistics, biostatistics, and data science. The writing workshop will provide individual hands-on guidance and mentoring by recent journal editors on how to write journal articles and research funding proposals.  Junior researchers will apply to the workshop by June 1 by submitting a writing sample and will be notified of acceptance no later than June 20 after pairing applicants with eight senior editors.  Previous workshops have been very successful with many workshop participants going on to become associate editors or co-editors of major statistical journals.  More specifically, at least 23 associate editorships and one co-editorship are among the 109 recent graduates from 2007 to 2011.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From 2007 to 2016, NISS organized technical writing workshops for junior researchers in statistics, biostatistics and data science. The 2018 NISS writing workshop consists of two parts. The workshop will open with tutorial sessions on the organization of material for a technical article or a grant application, on techniques for technical writing, and on the specific objectives and audiences of key journals in the statistical sciences. Another session will cover journal specific information for deciding where to publish, and a panel of current and recent editors will discuss the differences among the key journals.  Important ethical issues will also be discussed, and issues of journal choice, and understanding and responding to reviewers' comments will be covered in the final session.   At the end of this part, each participant meets with their mentor who analyzed a draft paper the participant submitted prior to workshop and receives feedback and suggestions.  The second part focuses on the specific issues for participants whose native language is not English, covering the writing process and details of grammar, sentence structure and word choice.  A panel of senior researchers whose native language is not English will discuss their experiences with technical writing in English.  The website for the workshop is:  &lt;br/&gt;https://www.niss.org/events/2018-niss-writing-workshop-junior-researchers-jsm&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833522</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosenberger</LastName>
<EmailAddress>JRosenberger@niss.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nell</FirstName>
<LastName>Sedransk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sedransk@niss.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lingzhou</FirstName>
<LastName>Xue</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lzxue@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Institute of Statistical Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Research Triangle Pk</CityName>
<ZipCode>277094006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196859300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 14006</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
