<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) Conference Student and Postdoc Travel Support</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rahul Shah</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports student attendance at the 59th IEEE Annual Symposium on the Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) in Paris, France from October 7 through October 9, 2018, as well as to support attendance by some qualified postdoctoral fellows who do not have other sources of travel funding. FOCS and its sister conference, the ACM STOC meeting, are the premier broad-based conferences on the Theory of Computing. FOCS has a record of strongly encouraging participation by students, for whom the conference serves as a valuable educational experience, both for the technical content of the talks and for the opportunities for networking that it provides. In recent years, the annual FOCS conference has been attended by eighty to one hundred students who have comprised more than a third of all attendees. This award will provide partial support to about 20 students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shanghua</FirstName>
<LastName>Teng</LastName>
<EmailAddress>shanghua@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
