<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Visitor Program in Set Theory, Model Theory, and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Each September and October the Logic Group at Rutgers University organizes a visitor program that attracts participants from all career stages from all over the world. The key goal of the program is to foster collaborations and to share ideas among researchers in the field of logic as well as related mathematical areas. The program, which also includes a series of seminars, has been very successful in generating many important research results. This award supports participation in the visitor program activities during 2018 - 2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary topics of the visitor program are set theory and model theory, and their applications to algebra and combinatorics. An important feature is the yearly involvement of Saharon Shellah, who is a leader in these fields of study. This award supports participation of approximately ten researchers each year, ranging from graduate students to leaders in the field, in a program that is a major asset for U.S. logic and contributes vigorously to the development of the subject on many levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833363</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
