<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>38th Southeastern-Atlantic Regional Conference on Differential Equations (SEARCDE)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports participation in the thirty-eighth annual Southeastern-Atlantic Regional Conference on Differential Equations (SEARCDE) at the University of North Georgia in Oakwood, Georgia, on October 6-7, 2018. Since its origin in 1981 at Virginia Tech, the conference has rotated among institutions in the southeast region of the United States. The main purpose of the conference is to promote research and education in the theory and applications of differential equations and the related numerical computations in many areas of science. Experts, beginning researchers, and graduate students will be brought together to share their research and develop a research network. Graduate students, university professors, and mathematicians who work in different industries from the southeastern region will particularly benefit from the conference; and women, minority, and underrepresented groups are strongly encouraged to participate in SEARCDE. Further information about the conference can be found at https://ung.edu/mathematics/searcde.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The goal of SEARCDE is to foster an environment for the exchange of ideas and the discussion of recent developments in the field. The thirty-eighth SEARCDE will focus on the application of differential equations in fluid dynamics, environmental change, and the related computational methods guiding high performance and parallel computing. Graduate students and beginning researchers will have opportunities to learn about progress in their field from experts, present their research, receive feedback, explore future directions, and develop collaborative projects. Three plenary speakers will deliver a one-hour lecture each at the conference, and all other participants will have an opportunity to present a twenty-minute talk on their research. There will also be an open forum led by experts that will foster discussion and collaboration among participants&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833126</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
