<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for Academically Talented STEM Scholars at the University of North Dakota</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>649791.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>649791</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project contributes to the national need for a highly-qualified STEM workforce by helping high-achieving, low-income STEM undergraduates with demonstrated financial need earn a STEM degree at the University of North Dakota.  Over its five-year duration, this project will provide one- to four-year scholarships to 31 students pursuing bachelor's degrees engineering, chemistry, biology, or aviation. By reducing or eliminating unmet educational costs, the scholarships can enable the Scholars to spend more time on their studies, as well as engage in experiences such as research projects and internships that are relevant to their long-term career interests. This project aims to create a professional development environment that promotes students' academic and professional success, so that the Scholars graduate with the skills needed to be successful STEM professionals or to obtain advanced STEM degrees. Consequently, the Scholars will be immersed in co-curricular training activities to promote learning and hone problem-solving skills. In addition, scholars will have access to academic support services and workshops with industry representatives or experts in career development.  Results of project research and evaluation will contribute to the knowledge base about effective recruitment, retention, and graduation of undergraduate STEM students in rural states.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the priority of North Dakota and the nation to retain undergraduates in STEM, thus producing scientifically literate citizens who can contribute to the security, technology development, and economic health of the state, the region, and the nation.  The outcomes of the project will contribute to the knowledge base about: (1) effective strategies for recruitment and retention of academically talented students from low-income and rural backgrounds to a STEM program at a rural four-year institution; (2) academic and professional development activities that promote student persistence and retention in STEM disciplines; (3) factors influencing STEM-related skill development and self-confidence for students from low-income backgrounds; (4) motivations for this group of students to study STEM; and (5) factors influencing STEM students' decision to pursue non-STEM careers. Many low-income students in North Dakota are of Native American descent, and it is expected that this project will elicit evidence-based strategies for retention and success of this group of students.  In addition, this project has the potential to broaden participation of rural students and Native Americans in STEM fields.  This project is funded by the NSF Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics program, which seeks to increase the number of low-income academically talented students with demonstrated financial need who earn degrees in STEM fields. It also aims to improve the education of future scientists, engineers, and technicians, and to generate knowledge about academic success, retention, transfer, graduation, and academic/career pathways of low-income students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833975</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>xiaodong.zhang@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia Xiaojun</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<EmailAddress>julia.zhao@email.und.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naima</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaabouch</LastName>
<EmailAddress>naima.kaabouch@engr.und.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Worley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>deborah.worley@und.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feng</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiao</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Feng.Xiao@engr.UND.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Dakota Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Grand Forks</CityName>
<ZipCode>582027306</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7017774151</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>264 Centennial Dr Stop 7306</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
