<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Naugatuck Valley's STEM Inclusive Opportunity Network</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>649323.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>649323</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pushpa Ramakrishna</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will contribute to the national need for a highly qualified STEM workforce by supporting the pursuit of a two-year STEM degree by 75 low-income students with demonstrated financial need and academic promise. The project will provide up to two years of scholarship support to students enrolled in associate-level degree programs in STEM fields, including Computer-Aided Design Engineering Technology, Computer information Systems Technology, Electronic Engineering Technology, Engineering Technology, Engineering Science, Environmental Science, Mechanical Engineering Technology, Technology Studies, Automated Manufacturing Engineering Technology, or a Biology, Chemistry, Computer Science Mathematics, or Physics Transfer Ticket degree.  The project intends to overcome cultural and institutional barriers to student success in STEM by providing Scholars with: strong social, academic, and professional support networks; diverse STEM role models;  enhanced STEM identity; training about overcoming adversity;  deeper knowledge of STEM career paths;  transitional education and orientation to college-level expectations; encouragement to use existing support systems;  and opportunities for professional development through research, internships, and job shadowing. The project also seeks to ensure student success beyond graduation through university transfer and job placement supports.  Given the diverse student population at the institution, this project could enhance the diversity of students who pursue STEM degrees. In addition, the large number of scholarships may have a significant impact on both the institution and the development of STEM graduates.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through implementation of a set of evidence-based practices, the project has the central goal of improving undergraduate student persistence and academic success in STEM fields. To evaluate the project's success in achieving this goal, project will conduct a quantitative and qualitative assessment to investigate how the project and its individual components affect STEM students' self-efficacy, motivation to pursue a STEM career, STEM identity, and persistence in obtaining a STEM degree. The project seeks to determine effective practices to promote student success, particularly for low-income underrepresented minority STEM students. These results could be valuable to other institutions that seek to develop faculty expertise in effective pedagogies and effective programming to support diverse students seeking STEM degrees.  This project is funded by the NSF Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics program, which seeks to increase the number of low-income, academically high-achieving students with demonstrated financial need who earn degrees in STEM fields. It also aims to improve the education of future scientists, engineers, and technicians, and to generate knowledge about academic success, retention, transfer, graduation, and academic/career pathways of low-income students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833974</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Angelastro</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pangelastro@nv.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Binney</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rbinney@nv.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marian</FirstName>
<LastName>Zerbi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mzerbi@nvcc.commnet.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Hepworth</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ehepworth@nv.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Naugatuck Valley Community College</Name>
<CityName>Waterbury</CityName>
<ZipCode>067083000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2035758044</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 Chase Parkway</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
