<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>National Association of Mathematicians Network of Opportunities Targeting Students and Faculty at HBCUs</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities - Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) supports conferences that seek to increase the research opportunities of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) students and faculty at HBCUs.  Morehouse College will host the National Association of Mathematicians' (NAM) conference to encourage undergraduate students to pursue advanced degrees in mathematics. The conference will be held at Morehouse College on September 28-30, 2018. About one hundred students from HBCUs, as well as mathematics faculty and researchers, will attend this conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Undergraduate MATHFest and the NAM Faculty Conference on Research and Teaching Excellence are the two featured events at the conference. Conference activities at MATHFest are designed to improve the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students as they complete their baccalaureate degrees and enter graduate programs and careers in STEM disciplines. Activities at the Faculty Conference are designed to strengthen mathematics education and research at HBCUs. A key objective is to provide undergraduate students the opportunity to interact with a group of mathematics researchers and teachers and to learn about opportunities in various fields of mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833234</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roselyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Roselyn.Williams@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edray</FirstName>
<LastName>Goins</LastName>
<EmailAddress>edray.goins@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ulrica</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>uwilson@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morehouse College</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4706390221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>830 Westview Drive S W</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
