<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Leveraging a STEM-focused Urban Industry Immersion Program to Expand Pathways for Undergraduates into STEM Fields</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>649855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>649855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to contribute to the national need for well-educated scientists, engineers, and technicians.  Over five years, this project will fund 20 scholarships to two groups of 10 students who are pursuing baccalaureate degrees in physics/engineering or biology. The project will support science and engineering students as they participate in a new urban-industry experiential immersion program.  This program includes undergraduate research, internships, class projects, job skills development, and opportunities for students to learn about careers in industry.  Student cohorts will be guided by faculty to foster strong connections with industry, and to help students develop job skills and knowledge about science and engineering-oriented careers.  Dissemination of the project will be facilitated by the Chicago Mayor's Office.  Recruitment will focus on students who are members of underserved populations and who are place-bound. Consequently, this project has the potential to broaden participation in STEM careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of the project are to: (1) recruit and enroll academically talented students with demonstrated financial need; (2) create a STEM-focused urban industry experiential learning cohort program; and (3) expand career pathways into the Chicago STEM-oriented (Science, Technology, Engineering, Mathematics) job market. In addition to providing scholarships and establishing a system of support for industry immersion experiences, the project will include an outcome-based evaluation study with a formative component to improve project implementation.  In addition, the project will conduct a research study that will conduct matched mixed methods comparative studies of the outcomes for Scholars relative to other students.  The research study will investigate the socioeconomic factors associated with student preparation, success, retention, and graduation. The findings from the evaluation and research studies will form the basis of a model for city-based learning in science and engineering for place-bound, underserved students in metropolitan areas. This project is funded by the NSF Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics program, which seeks to increase the number of low-income academically talented students with demonstrated financial need who earn degrees in STEM fields. It also aims to improve the education of future scientists, engineers, and technicians, and to generate knowledge about academic success, retention, transfer, graduation, and academic/career pathways of low-income students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1833769</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ray</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sdray@northpark.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/24/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<EmailAddress>embrown@northpark.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/24/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<EmailAddress>embrown@northpark.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/24/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<EmailAddress>egray@northpark.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sunshine</FirstName>
<LastName>Silver</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sunshinecsilver@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Park University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606254816</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7732445760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3225 W. Foster Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
