<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: 2018 DMR Young Investigators Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>105208</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical abstract&lt;br/&gt;Meeting of Young Investigators is organized to provide researchers with necessary information about NSF process, opportunities and mechanisms related to proposal submission. A group of first-time applicants or those who did not apply to NSF in the past will be provided helpful information designed to improve their proposal writing skills and understand the NSF process better. A mock proposal review activity will enable better understanding of the merit review process. Participation of PIs from small colleges and underrepresented groups was encouraged. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Participants of the DMR Young Investigators Workshop will receive information about the NSF process presented by current or past Program Directors. Specifically, the participants will be trained in Merit Review Principles, writing a successful proposal, building a strong Broader Impact component, Conflict of Interest and Ethics rules and they will learn about funding opportunities within NSF. Participants will write and review one-page proposals, to be evaluated by panels, including a full panel review process, discussion and writing panel summaries. The two-day intensive training obtained during the Workshop is expected to be most beneficial to young PIs and increase their chances of successful interactions with NSF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1834825</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yoonseok</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yoonslee@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
