<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Proposal in Support of the International Conference on Strength of Materials (ICSMA18)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2018 International Conference on Strength of Materials (ICSMA18) is one in a series of the most highly acclaimed topical conferences in the field of strength-of-materials. The focus areas for ICSMA18 are promoting topics at the very forefront of the field of mechanical behavior of materials.  Held every three years, it provides a unique forum for in-depth discussion of cutting-edge advances in the field and pathways to the future. This is the third time in its 50-year history that it will be held in the USA. There will also be two special symposia associated with the conference on dislocation theory and plasticity.  The organizers are emphasizing the interaction between junior and senior researchers in order to take advantage of the unique cross-section of attendees. A particular emphasis will be placed on encouraging and supporting the attendance and participation of students, post-doctoral associates and early career researchers.  The ICSMA18 will be held on July 14-18, 2018 at the Ohio State University campus in Columbus, Ohio.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technological development is paced by the creation and putting into service of materials that are ever-more capable of withstanding extreme conditions, such as high stress, temperature, radiation and long-term service. The International Conference on the Strength of Materials (ICSMA) has a 50 year tradition as the pre-eminent, independent, international venue for presentation of the latest advances in our understanding of the strength of materials. Scientific topics provide comprehensive coverage of the field, from basic concepts of deformation to advanced engineering materials, and across composites, alloys, biomedical and bio-inspired materials, and emerging materials. The meeting will advance fundamental understanding of the processes that govern the strength of materials at different length and time scales, and it will forge links between basic studies and investigations of technologically important engineering materials. Presentations will concern developments in state-of-the-art experimental techniques for evaluating material behavior and microstructure, and complementary computational and modeling efforts aimed at fundamental understanding of materials under these extreme conditions. The program has been designed to highlight the gaps in our knowledge, some of the more controversial recent developments, and unique new opportunities for exploiting developments in synthesis, characterization, property measurement and modeling for the creation of materials with enhanced performance and function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1834401</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Mills</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mills.108@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
