<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Core Support for the National Academy of Sciences' Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) and Chemical Sciences Roundtable (CSR)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>649635</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Divisions of Chemistry (CHE) and Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems (CBET) fund this award to the National Academy of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine. This award supports the core activities of both the Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) and the Chemical Sciences Roundtable (CSR). The results of BCST and CSR discussions and workshops are disseminated through workshop reports made available through professional societies, scientific and trade publications, and on the web. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BCST has broad representation from academe and industry and uses its collective expertise to identify the needs of the community.  The BCST provides peer-reviewed consensus reports, workshops, and symposia. The BCST enhances the impacts of the chemistry and chemical engineering communities by engaging in questions of importance to federal decision-makers. BCST members oversee a portfolio of ad hoc studies in key areas of education, workforce, and research issues. Specific areas of consideration for this funding period include: single cell/single molecule measurement, sustainable chemical manufacturing, quantum computing and its implications for chemistry, attracting and retaining student in undergraduate chemical education, incorporating new elements in chemical education such as data science and entrepreneurship. By raising issues impacting the conduct of chemistry and chemical engineering research with federal officials, BCST helps assure that the community of practitioners can remain at the forefront of knowledge. The CSR provides an apolitical forum for leaders in the chemical sciences and engineering, with the objective of enhancing understanding of issues that affect government, academic, national laboratory, and nonprofit sectors. CSR discussions provide a vehicle for interaction among the participants/  These participants discuss and report on education, exchange of information, and issues and trends that affect the chemical sciences. CSR engages leading scientists and engineers to identify and explore, through workshops, emerging topics of importance to the chemical community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1834303</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Fryberger</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tfryberger@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL INITIATIVES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
