<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DCL NSF INCLUDES: A National Summit to Survey and Stimulate  Broadening Participation Research at Historically Black and Tribal Colleges/Universities</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>246936.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246936</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Fay Cobb Payton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A National Summit to Survey and Stimulate Broadening Participation Research at Historically Black and Tribal Colleges/Universities&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The Quality Education for Minorities (QEM) Network and the QEM INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilot (DDLP) core partners is proposing Quad-C Broadening Participation (BP) a national summit in response to the National Science Foundation's Dear Colleague Letter 17-111. The two-day national summit on broadening participation of Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and Tribal Colleges and Universities (TCUs) in STEM Education Research will commence early Spring 2019, in the Washington, DC metropolitan area. The proposed Summit will create a platform for new collaborations within the NSF INCLUDES National Network, so participating institutions can cultivate shared goals, common metrics, and mutually reinforcing activities. The Summit's overall goal is to synthesize current knowledge of, and stimulate further collaborative research on, broadening participation of HBCU/TCU students in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). The Summit's key objectives will be to Convene, Connect, Collect, and Convey results (Quad-C) to reinforce the NSF INCLUDES National Network and the HBCU/TCU BPR Community of Practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1835082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>IVORY</FirstName>
<LastName>TOLDSON</LastName>
<EmailAddress>itoldson@qem.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026591818</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
