<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Traditional Knowledge of the Central and Upper Yukon Basin: Gathering Resiliency Data</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29223.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29223</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colleen Strawhacker</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Embedded within culture is wisdom about resilience that can support communities faced with rapid environmental and social change. This project will capture data and knowledge from the last generation of Tanana and Gwich'in Athabascan elders who were raised in tribal communities largely untouched by Western colonization.  This generation, now in their 70s, 80s, and 90s, are taking key knowledge and data sets with them as they die, leaving subsequent generations impacted by this loss of knowledge. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will document Indigenous Knowledge of resilience through a qualitative phenomenology framework in using semi-structured interviews conducted by community researchers with Indigenous elders of the Central and Upper Yukon Basin, born between the years 1920 and 1950. Primary research questions are:&lt;br/&gt;- How have adaptation strategies changed over a lifetime?&lt;br/&gt;- How did environmental changes trigger changes in community social structure?&lt;br/&gt;- What lessons about resilience can be learned from the generation that bridged the gap between largely traditional Athabascan lifestyle and Anglo-European colonization?&lt;br/&gt;Interviews will be conducted with up to six Elders from the central Yukon Athabascan region - a remote area that was one of the last areas in Alaska to experience colonization. This project is urgent as the Elders who are the subjects of this research project are near end of life with three of the original Elders identified for this project having passed away during the previous two years. Additionally, a rural, Alaskan Native person will be trained in the project methodology and taught to harness the tools of science in the preservation of culture. Products include a plain language report that will be geared toward Native Alaskans, and the collected information and data will be made available via a public repository for other Native Alaskans and scientific researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1835992</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maryann</FirstName>
<LastName>Fidel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mfidel@yritwc.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yukon River Inter-Tribal Watershed Council</Name>
<CityName>Anchorage</CityName>
<ZipCode>995012131</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9072583337</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>725 Christensen Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
