<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Assessing Ethics Education Interventions in Science and Engineering: Washington, D.C., August 2019</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49656.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49656</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Parker</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>For nearly a decade the National Science Foundation has required training in ethics and responsible conduct of research for postdocs, graduate students, and undergraduates who receive NSF funding, but much remains to be learned about the kinds of approaches to ethics education that are the most effective. Workshop participants will formulate a set of research questions for advancing the assessment of ethics training initiatives and then meet to answer these questions and advance collective understanding and practice related to ethics training assessments. Workshop results will contribute to developing a more robust evidence base for improving ethical sensitivity, clarifying ethical decision making, and fostering cultures of research integrity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will improve knowledge of factors affecting ethical decision making in research and of how to systematically assess the efficacy of research ethics training initiatives. Grant activities will be organized around developing answers to several research questions. These include: (1) What goals should ethics education interventions aim to achieve? (2) Which skills are essential to ethical decision making? 3) How can ethics education interventions contribute to a culture of integrity at the level of the individual, small group, and institution? (4) How can we best assess the efficacy and efficiency of different types of ethics education interventions? Workshop participants will collaborate to answer these questions and increase our ability to build and fairly assess next generation interventions for promoting research ethics. Results will be disseminated via conference proceedings and publications, while tools and assessment rubrics will be shared through The Online Ethics Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1835276</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Rourke</LastName>
<EmailAddress>orourk51@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Holbrook</LastName>
<EmailAddress>holbrook@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffmann</LastName>
<EmailAddress>michael.hoffmann@pubpolicy.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Briggle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>adam.briggle@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Heights</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>019Y</Code>
<Text>Cultivating Cultures of Ethica</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
