<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference:  2018 Gordon Research Seminar on Genomic Instability, to be held at Hong Kong University of Science and Technology in Kowloon, Hong Kong, July 21-22, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support attendance by graduate students and postdoctoral researchers at the Gordon Research Seminar on Genomic Instability: Chromosome Replication, Repair and Organization in the Maintenance of Genomic Stability, to be held at Hong Kong University of Science and Technology in Kowloon, Hong Kong, July 21-22, 2018. The meeting is organized and chaired by two early-career scientists.  The format of the meeting is a combination of talks and posters, which will promote scientific exchange in both formal and informal settings. A keynote lecture from a leading researcher in the field will be featured, together with a panel discussion on careers in science and a session on grant-writing.  There will be ample opportunity for sharing latest research results and for exploring collaborative possibilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will bring together scientists studying diverse topics related to genomic stability, including:  genome replication, repair and recombination; chromatin dynamics and chromosomal organization; and signaling in response to DNA lesions.  Cutting-edge and late-breaking research will be highlighted in short talks chosen from the abstracts and in posters. The primary purposes of this conference are to provide a venue for scientific exchange of new research results and ideas among young researchers, to foster learning about emerging trends and how they contribute to future goals for research on genomic instability, and to promote career development of a new generation of scientists, including those who are traditionally underrepresented in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1836557</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catalina</FirstName>
<LastName>Pereira</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cp556@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
