<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for the 256th National Meeting and Exposition of the American Chemical Society Symposium "Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly", Boston, MA (August 19-23, 2018)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL AND NONTECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Funds in the amount of $5000 are requested for support of US based participants in the symposium on "Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly", to be held as part of the ACS POLY Division at the  2018 National ACS meeting in Boston MA, August 18-22, 2018. The funds will be used to pay the meeting registration fees for postdoc, junior faculty, and other scientists in the early stages of post PhD independent research. The symposium will cover a broad array of topics in newest developments in block polymer synthesis, self-assembly , characterization and morphology. Emphasis will be given to presentations by junior workers in the field and their associated new directions with the goal of encouraging future STEM  development and people-power in the field.  The symposium includes both invited and contributed speakers. Of the sixteen invited speakers listed, two are postdocs, seven are assistant professors and two are from industry. Contributed papers include a majority from junior researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1836411</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lynd</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lynd@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
