<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integers Conference 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>23376.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>23376</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide funding for the "Integers Conference 2018," which will be held in Augusta, Georgia, October 3-6, 2018. The conference is being hosted by the Department of Mathematics at Augusta University. The Integers conferences, of which this will be the eighth, serve to bring together mathematicians and students interested in the fields of combinatorics and number theory. It will promote interaction among research mathematicians at all career stages from the talented undergraduate to the internationally distinguished researcher. A large portion of the funding will support students, early-career faculty, and mathematicians belonging to underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The conference will serve as a catalyst for major collaborative projects among mathematicians representing the areas of additive number theory, multiplicative number theory, combinatorial game theory, probabilistic number theory, enumerative combinatorics, combinatorial optimization, Ramsey theory, the theory of partitions, and other areas of combinatorics and number theory. It will feature three plenary speakers and around sixty additional speakers. The conference organizers plan to support twenty student research talks, including talks presented by students who have recently participated in an NSF "Research Experiences for Undergraduates" program. The proceedings of the conference will be published as a special volume of the journal Integers. The following website has been created for the conference:  https://sites.google.com/a/westga.edu/integersconference2018/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1836636</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
