<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Fifteen (15th) International Symposium on Equatorial Aeronomy (ISEA); Ahmedabad, India; October 22-26, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29848.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29848</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This conference grant requests funds to enable 14 students and young investigators to attend the 15th International Symposium on Equatorial Aeronomy (ISEA) in Ahmedabad, India during October 22-26, 2018. The ISEA is a major international conference held approximately quadrennially. Scientists from around the world gather to exchange ideas, plan observing campaigns, and listen to the latest scientific developments on the low-latitude atmospheric and ionospheric physics. Since 1972, presentations from all past workshops are published as part of special editions of peer-reviewed journals.  Scientific advances showcased at the ISEA advance understanding of ionosphere-thermosphere-magnetosphere coupling, and impacts upon communication and navigation. The location of the ISEA in India will encourage attendance from young researchers in developing nations in the Indian and African subcontinents and connect them to researchers from developed nations. Attendance of this conference can potentially lead a global, diverse workforce in the atmospheric and space sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1837033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Erickson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pje@haystack.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
