<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Support for the Academy of Management Organizational Communication and Information Systems 2018 Doctoral Consortium</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>28950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports travel of a diverse group of approximately 25 dissertation-stage students at U.S. institutions to participate in an international doctoral consortium with distinguished research faculty. The Organizational Communication and Information Systems (OCIS) doctoral consortium at the 2018 Academy of Management (AoM) convention in Chicago, Illinois, will consist of one and a half days of talks and interactions among OCIS students and researchers. The doctoral consortium provides students with feedback on their work from other students and faculty members, allowing them to enhance their own dissertation research proposals. Additionally, because of the diversity of the business sub-disciplines and communities involved in the AoM conference, the consortium will allow students to establish research connections beyond their own disciplines. Consequently, participation will allow students to develop a better understanding of the different research communities, which will facilitate their participation in future interdisciplinary research. In the past, the OCIS doctoral consortium has been a successful venue at which students can take major steps toward becoming professional researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The OCIS division at the annual AoM meeting provides a leading international forum for the presentation and discussion of research and practical issues related to the use and impact of information and communication technologies in organizations and society. The intellectual merit of this travel grant is that it provides a forum for doctoral students to exchange insights and receive feedback and guidance in order to enhance the quality of their dissertation research, and its broader impact lies in facilitating the establishment of new research collaborations and professional networks, as well as developing a greater awareness of ongoing cutting-edge research in the field of organizational communication and information systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1837239</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Gibbs</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gibbs@comm.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
