<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FAIR Publishing Guidelines for Spectral Data and Chemical Structures in Support of Chemistry and Related Disciplinary Communities</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24671</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beth Plale</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the PIs will convene a meeting to establish publishing guidelines for sharing machine-readable files of commonly reported chemical data classes.  The workshop organizers seek involvement from researchers, publishers, funding agencies, libraries, database and repository managers, tool developers, chemical societies, and standards organizations. Topics to discuss include formulating value propositions for data (that is, what data should be kept and for how long), and formulating criteria and stakeholder roles to better support data that are Findable, Accessible Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR).  Several outcomes are expected, including best-practice publishing guidelines specifying FAIR criteria for spectral and chemical structure data; and workflow models for capturing, managing and sharing these data in domain repositories. This workshop will build on momentum from the Research Data Alliance (RDA), the International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC), the American Chemical Society (ACS) and other related scientific societies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the National Science Foundation?s Public Access Initiative which is managed by the NSF Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure on behalf of the Foundation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1838960</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
<LastName>Scalfani</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vfscalfani@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
