<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshops on Mathematical Challenges in Many-Body Physics and Quantum Information</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for US participation for three workshops and a school that are part of the thematic program "Mathematical Challenges in Many-Body Physics and Quantum Information" to be held at Centre de Recherches Mathematiques (CRM) located in Montreal, Quebec, Canada.  The first workshop, "Quantum information and quantum statistical mechanics", will be held October 15-19, 2018.  The school  "Mathematics of Non-equilibrium Statistical Mechanics" will be held October 24-26, 2018.  The scond workshop, "Entropic fluctuation relations in mathematics and physics" will be held October 29-November 2, 2018.  The third workshop, "Spectral theory of quasi-periodic and random operators" will be held November 13-16, 2018.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The individual workshops and school focus on recent developments in Analysis, especially in the field of mathematical physics and quantum information science.  A number of distinguished mathematicians have agreed to attend and speak at this conference series.  This award gives early career researchers, members of underrepresented groups, researchers not funded by NSF and the like an opportunity to attend and participate in this conference. The organizing committee will strive to make this funding opportunity known to target groups through a number of different activities. More information will be made available at the thematic conference webpage: http://www.crm.umontreal.ca/Quantum2018/index.php/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1838991</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
