<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative: Mid-Atlantic Analysis Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of participants in the Mid-Atlantic Analysis Meeting that will be held on November 9-11, 2018, on the campus of Virginia Polytechnic and State University in Blacksburg, VA. Additional information about this meeting can be found at the website:  http://www.math.vt.edu/MAAM/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientific program of this conference is on the interactions of geometric measure theory, geometric functional analysis, harmonic analysis, operator algebras, probability theory and PDE. The meeting offers a strong program that includes plenary lectures by leading experts, short talks by early career mathematicians, poster sessions, and a career development panel. The conference activities are aimed at broadening participation in several of the most active areas of analysis. The conference program provides ample opportunity for graduate students, postdocs, and other young scientists to present their work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1838476</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
