<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support to Advance US Soil Science</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kendra McLauchlan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Soil is essential for human survival. Soil provides food, fiber, and ecosystem services. Understanding how soil functions therefore helps human society. In recognition of the importance of soils to all of humanity, the year 2015 was named the International Year of Soils. To further advance the understanding of soil and the services it provides, soil scientists have organized a meeting to discuss recent advances in knowledge. Students and early career researchers would benefit from attending this meeting. Additionally, scientists at this early career stage often have new ideas to contribute. Intensive training and mentoring in an early career stage will strengthen the U.S. workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide support for ten graduate students and early career scientists from the United States to present their research results at the 21st World Congress of Soil Science. This international meeting has the theme "Soil Science: Beyond Food and Fuel." It is expected to attract more than 5,000 scientists from all over the world. This project builds on a long tradition of supporting students and early career scientists in the field of soil science. This award will provide U.S. students and early career scientists a unique opportunity to showcase their research at the international level. The students and early career researchers will also receive high quality training. They will interact with leading soil scientists, hear about the latest scientific developments, and make valuable research connections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1839437</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>A. Ester</FirstName>
<LastName>Sztein</LastName>
<EmailAddress>esztein@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asmeret Asefaw</FirstName>
<LastName>Berhe</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aaberhe@ucmerced.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California - Merced</Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2092598670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5200 North Lake Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
