<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Aaniiih Nakoda Nic'-Mni' (Water) Center</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Regina Sievert</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the intellectual leadership of TCUP institutions so that they can address scientific or engineering needs or interests, specifically for their tribes or communities, or broadly for the Nation.  The TCU Enterprise Advancement Centers (TEA Centers) strand allows TCUP institutions to capitalize on their investments in STEM instructional and research capacity.  The Aaniiih Nakoda Nic'-Mni' (Water) Center ("the Center"), housed at Aaniiih Nakoda College (ANC), aligns with this TCUP goal in its research, education, and outreach work focusing on water quality and management issues relevant to the Fort Belknap Indian Community (FBIC). The Center builds on and expands a partnership between the college and the FBIC that has been focused on water quality monitoring and management for many years. The Center's research and outreach activities build the scientific knowledge base, increase public literacy, and inform the tribe's water management decisions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Aaniiih Nakoda Nic'-Mni' (Water) Center will conduct and integrate findings from four related water research studies on issues of critical concern to the FBIC; offer training and education programs that will provide community members with the knowledge, skills, experiences and credentials needed to address local water issues effectively; and gather and share information that can be used by the community to make informed decisions regarding the proper care and use of the reservation's water resources.  The research will include comparative bioassessments of surface water flowing onto the Fort Belknap reservation, principally through standardized biomonitoring methods that include protocols for benthic macroinvertebrates and periphyton; studies of local impacts on groundwater resources; and potential benefits of subsurface irrigation systems.  Training and education programs will target ANC students and FBIC employees, as well as other local stakeholders. ANC students will have opportunities for internships through the Center, and other individuals will have opportunities to participate in workshops and short courses.  The Center will also serve as a local clearinghouse for the community on water resource information.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1839859</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Friskics</LastName>
<EmailAddress>friskics@hotmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>McClain</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aquaticstudy@hotmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
<LastName>Werk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rwerk@ancollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Aaniiih Nakoda College</Name>
<CityName>Harlem</CityName>
<ZipCode>595260159</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 159</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
