<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference "Recent Advances in Functional Analysis"</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for US participation for the conference "Recent Advances in Functional Analysis", which will be held at Kent State University, Ohio, USA on October 11-14, 2018.   The conference focuses on recent developments in Analysis, especially in the field of functional analysis.  Presentation and discussion will concentrate on the specific topics of operator theory and geometry of Banach spaces, weighted bounds for Calderon?Zygmund operators, properties of Lipschitz mappings, asymptotic geometry of normed spaces, and probabilistic methods in functional analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award gives early career researchers, members of underrepresented groups, researchers not funded by NSF and the like an opportunity to attend and participate in this conference.  The organizing committee will strive to make this funding opportunity known to target groups through a number of different activities. More information will be made available at the conference webpage: http://www.math.kent.edu/RAFA2018/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1839058</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
