<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for Doctoral Students from U.S. Universities to Attend the 11th International Conference on Educational Data Mining (EDM 2018)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>19600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Cherniavsky</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support 10 doctoral students from the United States to attend the 11th Educational Data Mining (EDM) conference. Scheduled events include keynote talks by world-renowned researchers, full and short oral presentations, poster presentations, workshops, tutorials, interactive events, and the Doctoral Consortium (DC). The DC will include oral presentations and poster sessions in which students present their work. These sessions will be specially scheduled to prevent competition with other conference events and maximize attention by seasoned researchers. Students will be paired up with senior members of the EDM community who serve as mentors during the conference. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The EDM conference promotes scientific research in the interdisciplinary field of educational data mining, which is concerned with developing methods for exploring the unique types of data that come from educational settings, and using those methods to better understand students and the settings in which they learn.  EDM is the convergence of computer science disciplinary research in databases and data mining and learning science. EDM research activities are aimed at applying data mining to analyze data generated by various information systems that support learning or education (in schools, colleges, universities, and other academic or professional learning institutions and informal learning).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1840771</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
<LastName>Heffernan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nth@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8020</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>W-HTF Work at the Human-Technology Front</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8045</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
