<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FW-HTF: First Person View and Augmented Reality for Airborne Embodied Intelligent Cognitive Assistants</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>1500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Miller</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Future of Work at the Human-Technology Frontier (FW-HTF) is one of 10 new Big Ideas for Future Investment announced by NSF. The FW-HTF cross-directorate program aims to respond to the challenges and opportunities of the changing landscape of jobs and work by supporting convergent research. This award fulfills part of that aim. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The future of work will involve human operators and semi-autonomous robotic systems. Human workers control the robots, extending their sensing and physical capabilities. This technology-empowered workforce will do remote, dangerous, and increasingly specialized work. An example use of this work might be the inspection of hard-to-access bridge supports. This project will explore the use of intelligent airborne drones to help ground-based operators in the inspection of highway bridges. Through the careful integration of augmented reality (AR) with first-person-view (FPV) operator interfaces this research will enhance worker performance across a wide range of otherwise very difficult tasks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research program will address key challenges in the use of embodied intelligent cognitive assistants (e-ICAs) for infrastructure inspection. New principles of shared situation awareness will be developed for human/robot collaboration through AR/FPV user interfaces and these principles will inform interface design guidelines and evaluation measures. The research program will also emphasize collaborative perception and planning, such as peripheral/central computer vision to enhance shared situation awareness, gaze-informed adaptive viewpoint planning for improved image quality, and a global planning method for partially known and uncertain maps that adapts the plan in real-time as the worker discovers new information. Tunable control system performance will allow the worker and the e-ICA to collaborate in managing disturbance energy to optimize mission data quality and flight endurance while ensuring safety of flight. The parallel development of a public repository containing annotated deterioration imagery will support artificial intelligence based defect analytics to provide the human worker with real-time inspection cues. A parallel and coordinated economic and workforce analysis will assess the impact of airborne e-ICAs, controlled using FPV with augmented reality, on the future of work in infrastructure inspection and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1840044</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Hebdon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mhebdon@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Woolsey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cwoolsey@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Gabbard</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jgabbard@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pratap</FirstName>
<LastName>Tokekar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tokekar@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>082Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF: Advancing Cognitive an</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>W-HTF Work at the Human-Technology Front</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
