<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference; 2018 Centromere Biology GRS; July 28-29, 2018; West Dover, Vermont</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10450</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support the attendance of early career researchers at the Gordon Research Seminar on Centromere Biology, which will be at on July 28-29 2018 at the Mount Snow Center in West Dover, Vermont.  The format of the meeting is a combination of talks and posters, which will promote scientific exchange in both formal and informal settings. One session is devoted to the professional development and mentoring of early career scientists. There will be ample opportunity for sharing the latest research results and for networking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Centromere is a region on a eukaryotic chromosome at which the kinetochore is assembled. Kinetochore and centromere to which it attaches jointly drive chromosome movement during cell division. This conference establishes centromere biology as a distinct field of study with a coherent research community, working across scales from understanding protein assembly and biochemical pathways to defining patterns of inheritance. A specific aim of this research seminar is to provide young scientists with a welcoming environment and provide an opportunity to actively and openly discuss their research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1840251</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Straight</LastName>
<EmailAddress>astraigh@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
