<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Workshop Proposal for Shared Teaching Materials for Advanced Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>59817.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>59817</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The manufacturing of three&amp;#8208;dimensional products from computer&amp;#8208;driven digital models has found extensive applications in several fields. These additive manufacturing technologies offer the possibility to fabricate products at affordable prices and have been employed to make customized, complex items. North Carolina State University in collaboration with Iowa State University is requesting funding for a  collaborative workshop proposal titled "A Workshop Proposal for Shared Teaching Materials for Advanced Manufacturing ". The goal of the proposal is to run a series of well organized, impactful workshops to catalyze the creation of a central repository for state-of-the-art curricular materials that will facilitate authoring, evaluating and disseminating materials for advanced manufacturing education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs have previously developed customizable teaching materials and shared them with colleagues.  These materials will be used as the basis for the repository.  The plan for each workshop is to assemble groups of engineers, technologists and faculty involved in manufacturing to discuss the use and adoption of these materials.  The workshops are intended to 1) critique the proposed "organic materials" concept; 2) obtain buy-in from the manufacturing community; and 3) identify early adopters and developers to help develop a future collaborative IUSE proposal. The duration of each workshop, one of which will be co-located with a professional manufacturing meeting, will be approximately half a day.The project focus on the development of state-of-the-art curricular materials aligns well with the goals of the IUSE E&amp;D program in the Engaged Student Learning track.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1841320</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gul</FirstName>
<LastName>Okudan Kremer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gkremer@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/11/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
