<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Student Travel Support Request for the IFAC Conference on Cyber-Physical &amp; Human Systems 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal is for support of student travel for the 2nd International Federation of Automatic Control (IFAC) Conference on Cyber-Physical and Human Systems being held in Miami, Florida.   The conference is sponsored by the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers.  The focus on integration of Human and Cyber-Physical Systems is an area of great importance and direct applicability to NSF's Cyber-Physical Systems and Smart and Connected Communities Programs.   The award will provide travel support for approximately 10 graduate students to attend, present papers, and participate in conference activities.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This conference will provide the students with the opportunity to attend presentations of cutting-edge research results representing the state-of-the-art in cyber physical systems and their integration with humans.   The attendees are offered a diversity of interactive forums, technical sessions, targeted workshops, interesting poster sessions, and exciting demonstrations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1841832</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tansel</FirstName>
<LastName>Yucelen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yucelen@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
