<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Ecosystem Management - Selective Insect Control</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the improvement to public health from improved containment of aerial insect-borne diseases and decreased use of toxic pesticides. Traditional, chemical pest-control methods are imprecise, causing damage after they have been applied. This technology creates the option for controlled extermination, which in turn can prevent an imbalanced predator-prey relationship and ultimately the unintended collapse of symbiotic populations, such as bat/birds. Moreover, it does not pose threats to human safety from chemical contamination of air or water supply, or even residue ingested via harvested crops. This project could also combat serious public health risks, such as Zika, by eliminating carriers in populated areas. This benefit would also hold appeal for those in sports and leisure applications by reducing pests at stadiums or while enjoying activities such as hiking or fishing. Based on disruptive technology, this team hopes to provide these benefits at a lower cost than present pest-control or healthcare solutions, based on the precision level and expanded area of effect. This generates economic gains and the possibility of exporting products to be competitive in markets with reduced means while supporting American intellectual property. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is formed around a disruptive technology in the pest control and ecosystem management space. More concisely, it is a green and cheaper alternative to traditional chemical pest control that can capture invasive and harmful species of flying insects without harming or otherwise affecting non-targeted species. This technology has commercial applications in agricultural, leisure, residential, and health management (disease control) sectors. This work would determine the need for highly effective and thorough collection and containment of disease carrying flying insects by agencies responding to threats such as Zika virus. The team would also like to explore the large footprint agricultural sector to see if this could be a viable-and preferable- alternative to traditional pesticides. Products derived from this project will be capable of the target and capture of specific flying insects and utilize advanced manufacturing methods in optics and electronics, as well as enabling enhanced sampling for those studying insect species. In summary, this green, portable, specialized technology has superior environmental benefits and can potential provide superior pest control at a reduced cost from traditional, and more harmful, alternatives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1842103</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gold</FirstName>
<LastName>Hood</LastName>
<EmailAddress>goldie.hood@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
