<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symposium: Advances in Intermetallic-Based Alloys for Structural &amp; Functional Applications; 2018 Materials Research Society Fall Meeting; Boston, Massachusetts; 25-30 November</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intermetallic compounds are an integral part of materials design for structural and functional applications and understanding their behavior is critical to improved performance. Extensive research has been underway to understand the fundamental aspects of intermetallics and the knowledge base is continuously evolving. Nevertheless, significant knowledge gaps exist in the fundamental science of intermetallics, as well as in processing and scale-up for eventual application. This award supports a symposium on fundamental understanding of the processing, microstructure, and properties of these materials at the Materials Research Society (MRS) Fall Meeting in Boston, Massachusetts, November 25-29, 2018. This symposium series was started in 1984 and is one of the longest running symposia in MRS history.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will enable the attendance at the symposium of graduate students, post-doctoral researchers, early career faculty and researchers from underrepresented groups. Support for students and early career researchers for travel and registration at the MRS meeting is a critical part of broadening and educating the field of researchers, as well as advancing knowledge and information exchange about this important class of materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1843435</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
<LastName>Dillen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewandowski</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jjl3@case.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL INITIATIVES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
