<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Effects of Teaching Practices on Peer Victimization and Defending Behaviors</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>678049.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>678049</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chalandra Bryant</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Peer victimization negatively impacts academic, psychological, and physiological functioning in children. Studies have shown that whether and how children defend their victimized peers has a significant impact on the adjustment of victims. Although much research has focused on individual factors and on class-level dynamics of victimization, less is known about the role of teachers. This project will examine the complex ways in which teachers' characteristics, practices, and actions affect (1) students' beliefs and attitudes; (2) the classroom ecology; and (3) victimization and defending behaviors. Future researchers will be able to use these findings to develop teacher training programs. Findings may also facilitate the development of anti-bullying policies and classroom management strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will address the following research questions: What is the association between teaching practices and peer victimization? What is the association between teaching practices and students' desires to defend their victimized peers? How do teaching practices contribute to students' attitudes toward victimization, and are these associations a function of the quality of teacher-student relationships?  Social motivation theoretical models provide an important interpersonal context for socialization by teachers whereas social cognitive theory describes how socialization might contribute to student social cognition and the classroom climate. The researchers will examine reciprocal interactions between teachers and students in fourth and fifth grade classrooms. The project will use a short-term longitudinal design.  Multimethod (e.g., surveys, in-class observations) and multi-informant (teachers, students, trained observers) approaches will be used to gather unique data for multilevel analyses. The use of observational methodology will facilitate capturing teacher-classroom practices as well as teacher-student relations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844510</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheri</FirstName>
<LastName>Bauman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sherib@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jina</FirstName>
<LastName>Yoon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jinayoon@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
<LastName>Toomey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>toomey@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS - Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DEVELOP&amp; LEARNING SCIENCES/CRI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
