<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STEM+C Education Research Summit</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>438647.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438647</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arlene de Strulle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The STEM+C Program focuses on research and development of interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary approaches to the integration of computing within science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) teaching and learning for preK-12 students in both formal and informal settings. The Education Development Center (EDC) will develop and facilitate a STEM+C Education Research Summit that will support the STEM+C research community to collect, share, and analyze their research findings; address NSF's Big Ideas in computational STEM fields; and because of the powerful innovation and application of computing in the STEM disciplines, the Summit will continue to catalyze the research field for advancing real-world, interdisciplinary, and computational preparation of students from the early grades through high school.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The STEM+C Research Summit design will be drawn from literature on best practices of innovation networks and communities of practice (COPs) to foster the development of a STEM+C innovation COP. The COP meeting design and facilitation will give PIs an opportunity to expand on their work and explore the confluence of issues and overlaps within the STEM+C community. To encourage a research culture that is globally engaged, an international panel of STEM+C researchers will be invited to present their research on advances in STEM+C in various countries. The Summit will be a working meeting, during which STEM+C community members will learn about advances made by community members, synthesize findings around emerging research themes, and identify and/or recommend new directions for STEM+C research. Working groups organized around emerging themes will represent a nexus of intellectual work that provides opportunities for PIs to deepen understandings and relationships in those areas. Outcomes of the Summit will include, development of a unique, interdisciplinary community of practice; collectively producing artifacts and products; increased understanding of the findings of STEM+C research projects; advancement of STEM+C evaluation methods to build expertise in designing research that will lead to viable outcomes as the foundation for education innovation; develop professional peer connections leading to future research collaborations; provide opportunities to engage in syntheses research activities and ongoing articulation of program-wide findings and lessons learned; and participation in a working group that will address future strategies for STEM+C education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844719</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Malyn-Smith</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Jmalynsmith@edc.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarita</FirstName>
<LastName>Nair-Pillai</LastName>
<EmailAddress>spillai@edc.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Education Development Center</Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<ZipCode>024538313</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176182227</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>43 Foundry Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
