<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Geo Futures Program: A Workshop for Undergraduates: Oct 30-Nov 2, 2019 - Honolulu, HI</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>98471</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Conferences provide students with a scaffolding experience that enhances their understanding of the culture of STEM while also helping them develop a peer network that enhances their identity in science. Set within the annual Society for the Advancement of Chicanos and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) Conference, a national conference that specifically engages with the cultural structures of students from underrepresented groups, this workshop will pilot engagement strategies for recruiting, engaging, and retaining a diverse assemblage of students. This workshop will provide forty undergraduate students with support and mentorship that is important for their retention in STEM fields, particularly in the geosciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A workforce with diverse perspectives will be required to address the emerging needs of 21st century geosciences. A primary goal of the workshop is to support the new generation of geoscientists that includes students from underrepresented groups and students with diverse backgrounds. Forty undergraduate students and approximately fifteen mentors will participate in the week-long workshop and the SACNAS conference in October, 2019. The workshop contributes to NSF's "Strategic Objective 2.2 : STEM Workforce: Foster the growth of a more capable and diverse research workforce and advance the scientific and innovation skills of the Nation." (NSF Strategic Plan for Fiscal Years 2018-2022)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844401</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corey</FirstName>
<LastName>Garza</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cogarza@csumb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation at Monterey Bay</Name>
<CityName>seaside</CityName>
<ZipCode>939558001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8315823089</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Campus Center</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017Y</Code>
<Text>Polar Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6899</Code>
<Text>OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
