<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>11th North American Paleontological Convention: Conference Support: Riverside, CA - June 23 to June 27, 2019</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dena Smith</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The eleventh North American Paleontological Convention (NAPC) is being held at the University of California, Riverside (UCR) from June 23 to June 27, 2019. NAPC is a large, international meeting attended every five years by scientists, students, and amateurs who study the history of life in the universe. During NAPC, attendees are presenting and discussing scientific findings, defining directions for future research and outreach, and are mentoring/being mentored by professionals and peers. Symposia, workshops, and field trips are being held throughout the conference. Funds are going towards the travel and housing costs for 100 students to attend NAPC. NAPC activities are advancing discovery and understanding, broadening participation of under-represented groups, and broadening dissemination to enhance scientific and technological understanding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NAPC is a forum where hundreds of scientists from around the world can formally and informally exchange information, mentor, and create contacts. Topical sessions, workshops, and field trips on a wide range of research areas, including astrobiology, paleogenomics, paleoclimatology, and conservation paleobiology, are being convened. A plenary session emphasizes the importance of deep time studies among the public. UCR is a Hispanic Serving Institution, and several activities were designed to promote diversity and inclusion within the paleontological subdisciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844858</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Droser</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mary.droser@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nigel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hughes</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nigel.hughes@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
