<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Statistics Curriculum at a Crossroads</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>68378.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>68378</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Funding from this award will support the workshop "Graduate Statistics Education at a Crossroads", to be held November 2-3, 2018 in Alexandria, VA.  The workshop will identify challenges and barriers that limit graduate statisticians from fully participating in the new era of big data.  To address these challenges and barriers, workshop attendees will craft realizable recommendations for academic departments and institutions. It is expected that these recommendations will promote model curricula, pedagogical approaches, and innovative approaches that have the potential to foster broader engagement with data science and to promote success of future statisticians in data science research and the workforce more broadly. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop aligns with the training aspects of Harnessing the Data Revolution, one of ten big ideas for future NSF investment. More specifically, the workshop aims to identify an array of data-science related training activities that would support the statistics community in order that statisticians fully participate in cutting-edge interdisciplinary data science research. Additional details may be found at https://hub.ki/groups/statisticsgraduateeducation/overview&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844975</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
