<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Replenishing the Skin Microbiome</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pamela McCauley</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is based on its focus on promoting balanced human microflora. The project aims at commercial development of a novel prebiotic and probiotic skincare line to improve skin appearance and overall health. Considering the increasing recognition of the importance of microflora in human health and the growing demand for natural products, the focus is on developing prebiotic and probiotic skincare product lines to fit within the $10-billion+ organic beauty market. However, the approach has broader implications for the general skincare and healthcare markets. Currently, most treatments for skin conditions such as eczema and psoriasis ignore the bacterial component, instead utilizing harsh chemical and invasive solutions. If successful, efforts will ultimately shift toward more intrinsic and natural solutions that aid the body in healing itself, without contributing to further disruption of skin integrity. As the skin and its associated bacteria contribute to defending the body against environmental contaminants and foreign invaders, the approach also paves the way for novel prebiotic and probiotic products for promoting robust immune function. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project focuses on the use of skin-associated microorganisms to improve overall appearance and health. Beneficial bacteria exist on the human body, helping it function properly and protecting it from various diseases. The skin is the largest organ of the immune system and the first line of defense against toxins and pathogens; the presence of beneficial skin bacteria is essential not only for appearance, but also for overall human health. The bacteria exist on the skin as cooperating, surface-attached communities. A balance of specific bacterial species, as well as proper attachment to the skin, is essential for the protective beneficial functions of these communities. Disruption of the microflora balance and/or of bacterial attachment to the skin can result in a variety of disorders. To promote skin health, the investigators have identified specific beneficial skin bacteria, as well as factors that promote the establishment of the functional bacterial communities--in particular, naturally produced factors that promote the attachment of bacteria to biotic surfaces, such as the skin. Based on those results, they have developed a system to balance the skin microbiome that utilizes proprietary probiotic formulations containing live skin-associated bacteria and prebiotic factors, which promote the interactions of these bacteria with the skin.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1844789</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
<LastName>Petrova</LastName>
<EmailAddress>opetrova@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
