<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symposium: Nanomaterials and Nanomanufacturing for Sustainability; 2018 Materials Research Society Fall Meeting; Boston, Massachusetts; 25-30 November 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10270</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is for the partial support for the Nanomaterials and Nanomanufacturing for Sustainability Symposium at the Fall Materials Research Society (MRS) Meeting in Boston, Massachusetts, 25-30 November 2018. The award provides funds for the conference travel and registration expenses of graduate students, postdocs, early career faculty, and underrepresented minority and women researchers. The MRS Meeting is the premier international conference, where academic, government laboratory and industry representatives participate, speak and discuss topics in advanced materials and manufacturing. This Symposium's topic is Sustainable Nanotechnology, with a specific focus on Nanomaterials and Nanomanufacturing. The Symposium advances knowledge in in emerging and advanced nanomaterials and nanomanufacturing for sustainability and environment, which impacts the nation's prosperity and health. The Symposium is a networking and workforce development opportunity by providing a forum for students and young faculty to meet attendees from industry, government labs and other academic institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Nanomaterials and Nanomanufacturing for Sustainability Symposium's goal is to advance knowledge in emerging and advanced nanomaterials and nanomanufacturing for cleaner, more efficient technologies for transportation, energy management, environmental monitoring and depollution. The topics are nanomaterials and nanomanufacturing for sustainability; air, soil and water quality management; renewable energy; lighter and stronger materials; nanotoxicology; and life cycle analysis. The symposium is a venue for tutorials, keynote lectures, oral and poster presentations, and networking for students, faculty and industry. It is a forum to learn new methods and exchange research results. A novel sub-event involves rapid-fire presentations to give an opportunity to all poster presenters to pitch their poster for 1 minute during the oral sessions and on a LCD screen next to the outside signage of the session. Winning pitches are recognized.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1846628</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
<LastName>Dillen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>MONICA</FirstName>
<LastName>JUNG DE ANDRADE</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mxj105120@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL INITIATIVES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
