<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:Towards the First Astronomical Catalog of Neutrino Sources</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>748708.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>157491</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In July 2018, IceCube announced compelling evidence of the first astronomical high-energy neutrino source.  Through this multi-messenger effort, one learns that in order to become a true partner in multi-messenger astronomy, neutrinos need to resolve more than a handful of sources to understand which source types are dominant, and neutrinos must be sensitive enough on their own to make statements about these sources. With those goals in mind, this award develops a new channel of source localization analysis using IceCube data, namely cascade events, that is completely independent of the ones used in traditional source searches. This has the potential of doubling IceCube's source search capacity. A planned upgrade of the detector will further enhance the sensitivities of cascade analyses, making the development of this analysis channel an urgent priority. Establishing the first catalog of high-energy neutrino sources will make neutrinos a powerful and integral part of multi-messenger astronomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IceCube experiment provides diverse, yet accessible science topics suitable for undergraduate and post-bac research. The PI has a long record of public outreach that will continue with this program. The PI recognizes that the practice of inclusion in a research environment, such as a large collaboration, will ultimately result in better science. She understands the impact she can have, particularly on young women and girls, by simply being a visible face of a physicist. She is committed to carrying out an effective and meaningful science program as well as an impactful broader impacts program through IceCube.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1847827</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
