<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>U.S. Participation in International Geoscience Unions: IUSS, INQUA, IUGS, and IUGG</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>573080.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>573080</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support the National Academies of Sciences (NAS), Board on International Scientific Organizations (BISO) to represent the relevant US science communities through separate National Committees (USNC) to four, individual International Geoscience Unions that are part of the International Science Council (ISC). These unions are the International Union of Soil Sciences (IUSS), the International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA), the International Union of Geological Sciences (IUGS), and the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics (IUGG).  The main role of each U.S. National Committee (USNC) is to facilitate participation of American scientists in the activities of its respective union and to "advance US visibility and impact globally through the engagement, collaboration, and leadership of international scientific societies".  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The USNC for Soil Science will work to advance U.S. soil science through topical symposia and national conferences and aid in the development of early career scientists through exposure to international soil science research at the World Congress of Soil Sciences.  The USNC for Quaternary Research will play an important role in the scientific content of the 2019 International INQUA Congress and will organize topical sessions at U.S. professional society meetings on the future of and vision for Quaternary Research.  The USNC for Geological Sciences will support the development of a more inclusive geologic workforce.  The USNC for Geodesy and Geophysics will focus on nominating U.S. scientists for union leadership positions and will increase outreach to the geophysical and geodetical communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1848740</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
