<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Very Long Baseline Array Fiber Optics Data Access Supplement</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph E. Pesce</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal describes plans to complete the connection of all VLBA stations to an optical fiber network.  Upon completion the VLBA data network capacity will be increased to 200 Mbps.  Such capacity will allow improved diagnostic and time-critical observing capabilities.  Upgrades to the VLBA data network is the first step in a three-phased approach to allow real-time observations.  Improved connectivity that optical fiber provides will increase the scientific utility of the VLBA for the US and global scientific community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Improving the data capabilities of the VLBA by installing/operating optical fiber to all sites will greatly enhance its capabilities, opening additional areas of VLBA research and extend the distance ranges, both within the Galaxy and throughout the Universe, at which the VLBA can make unique scientific contributions.  The VLBA is uniquely situated to increase participation of traditionally under-served and underrepresented communities in the full spectrum of fields associated with radio astronomy. With 10 sites located across eight states and the U.S. Virgin Islands, the VLBA offers research and educational exchange opportunities to a broad cross section of the U.S. student population, including students who live and study in areas of the country in which targeted efforts are made to broaden participation of diverse individuals in STEM education, training, and professional development.  In addition, VLBA observations are vital to maintaining awareness of Earth's orientation in space, a parameter of key importance in operation of the Global Positioning System for example.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1849364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Beasley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tbeasley@nrao.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>acohen@aui.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Associated Universities Inc/National Radio Astronomy Observatory</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200366225</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024621676</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 16TH ST NW STE 730</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>046F</Code>
<Text>NRAO-OPERATIONS &amp; MAINTENANCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
