<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HBCU Computer Science Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>113340.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>113340</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Fay Cobb Payton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Science Foundation's (NSF) Directorate for Computer and Information Science and&lt;br/&gt;Engineering (CISE) is committed to broadening the participation of underrepresented populations in&lt;br/&gt;computing and closely-related disciplines. Indeed, CISE strongly encourages meaningful actions that&lt;br/&gt;address the longstanding underrepresentation of various populations including women, minorities&lt;br/&gt;(African Americans/Blacks, Hispanic Americans, American Indians, Alaska Natives, Native Hawaiians,&lt;br/&gt;Native Pacific Islanders, and persons from economically disadvantaged backgrounds), and persons with&lt;br/&gt;disabilities, in the computing field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Unfortunately, only a few (or no) historically black colleges and universities (HBCUs) have participated in proposal submission/awardees to broadening participation in computing since 2012. Even though there are newer NSF programs, such as Computing Education for 21st Century (CE21) along with Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics-Computing (STEM-C) Partnerships, there are still few proposals submitted by and awarded to HBCUs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will enable HBCU computer science/computing faculty to collaborate and address the needs associated with broadening participation and create cross-institutional strategies to increase research outcomes. Workshop participants will engage in post-workshop meetings at CS conferences and virtually to increase the level of accountability associated with NSF grantsmanship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1849541</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chutima</FirstName>
<LastName>Boonthum</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chutima.boonthum@hamptonu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Muhammad</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeana.muhammad@hamptonu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hampton University</Name>
<CityName>Hampton</CityName>
<ZipCode>236680108</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7577275363</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 E. Queen Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055Y</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041Z</Code>
<Text>HBCU-Strengthening Research Capacities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
