<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A New Bio-based Monomer for the Coatings Industry</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224752.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224752</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project lies in the replacement of key petroleum-based chemicals used in the paints and coatings industry, representing a $7B industry that is growing at 7% per year. The total addressable market includes 3 similar diols: 1,4-butanediol (1,4-BDO), 1,5-pentanediol (1,5-PDO), and 1,6-hexanediol (1,6-HDO). In this project, 1,5-PDO is produced from furfural, a chemical made from renewable agricultural residues such as corn cobs and wood chips.  Bio-based 1,5-PDO can be readily substituted for 1,6-HDO in many applications due to its analogous molecular structure and is similar enough to 1,4-BDO that it can be substituted for it in some applications. Rigorous technoeconomic analysis shows that this "green" 1,5-PDO can be made at 3x lower costs than oil-derived 1,5-PDO, opening new opportunities for its use as a renewable monomer for paints, coatings, adhesives and plastics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project will allow the technology to be developed with commercially available fixed bed pellet catalysts to prepare the technology for scale-up.  Thus far, the technology has been demonstrated in small scale fixed bed reactors with powder catalysts.  A commercial scale process requires the use of pelletized catalysts due to inoperable pressure drops over powder catalysts in commercial-scale reactors. The higher flowrates inherent with larger scale reactors cannot flow through the tightly packed powder catalysts and cause a large degree of backpressure upstream of the catalyst bed; thus, pelletized catalysts must be sourced from commercial vendors and tested for activity and stability prior to scaling.  The next phase in technology development is to scale up the process by &gt;100x, enabling testing and validation of larger amounts of the bio-based 1,5-PDO product in potential customers' product lines.  This SBIR Phase I project will also allow completion of the process design work needed to estimate the economics at commercial scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1849600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Barnett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kjbarnett@pyranco.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PYRAN LLC</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537033590</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2148863260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>309 W WASHINGTON AVE UNIT 406</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
