<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EFRI-2DARE and NewLAW Grantees Meeting Workshop, San Diego, October 17-19, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>58696</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed project seeks financial support to support a workshop to be held October 17-19, 2018 at the Sheraton San Diego Hotel and Marina CA.  The Workshop will bring together the NSF EFRI Two- Dimensional Atomic-Layer Research and Engineering (2-DARE), as well as New Light, EM (Electronic) and Acoustic Wave Propagation: Breaking Reciprocity and Time Reversal Symmetry (NewLAW) supported researchers working on materials and devices in these areas to help promote future collaborations and address common challenges. This includes faculty, postdoctoral researcher and graduate students from the institutions supported by the 2-DARE and NewLAW programs. The Workshop is expected to play a key role in addressing in detail currently faced bottlenecks in material and device research and identifying new directions for research.  The research discussed at the Workshop is expected to lead to technological breakthroughs and disruptive technologies that can have great societal impact in the future in many areas such as sensing, communications and health.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1849079</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuanxun</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ywang@ee.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
