<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Seminar on Stochastic Processes 2019</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pawel Hitczenko</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2019 Seminar on Stochastic Processes (SSP) will be held at the University of Utah in Salt Lake City, UT from March 13-16, 2019. This conference has been held annually since 1981 and is devoted to probability theory and stochastic processes. Past conferences have had major impact on the field in several distinct ways. They consistently feature broad participation of graduate students and early-career researchers, including future Fields medalists and other world-leading experts in the early stages of their research careers. The primary goal is to provide a platform for the dissemination of the most significant recent research progress in the theory of stochastic processes, and to enable participants to discuss ideas in an informal atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stochastic processes are basic building blocks of the way that randomness exhibits itself in the real world, and are used to model a wide range of physical, biological, ecological, and financial phenomena. The format of this meeting is based on the success of recent Seminars on Stochastic Processes. There will be five one hour talks and a tutorial session consisting of two 90 minute lectures, all delivered by distinguished speakers on key recent themes and developments in stochastic processes research. Talks also emphasize the important connections of stochastic processes to other parts of mathematics and the sciences. There will also be a poster session and opportunities for early career researchers to present their own research, and time set aside for the discussion of open problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More details are available at the conference website&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.math.utah.edu/SSP-2019/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1850630</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
