<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research in Astrophysics at the Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>401040.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>401040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Benacquista</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory will continue its long-running summer REU (Research Experiences for Undergraduates) program. In addition to a 10-week summer research internship working with scientists at the Harvard/Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA), students will engage in numerous professional development activities, including computer tutorials, research-training seminars, and directed meetings with astrophysicists at all career stages. Students will also attend group discussions on the ethical conduct of research, graduate school life, admissions, available fellowships, and career opportunities after graduation. Since 1994, over half of the interns have been female, and a small but increasing number from underrepresented groups. During this renewed program greater emphasis will be placed on recruiting students from underrepresented groups as well as from colleges with limited resources for astrophysical research. This site is supported by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each summer, eleven students will spend ten weeks conducting leading-edge research with their mentors at CfA. Scientists at the CfA are involved in virtually every area of astrophysics and have access to a large number of modern scientific instruments, so students have a broad range of projects to choose from. The student research experience will be completed by a trip to the winter AAS meeting, where each intern will present a poster.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1852268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Ashby</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mashby@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/14/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174967923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Garden St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1219</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>S153</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
