<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Broadening Undergraduate Research Participation in Physics and Astronomy at Stony Brook University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>273308.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>273308</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the Research Experience for Undergraduates site at SUNY at Stony Brook.  The site will support six students in year one, and eight in the following two years, for ten weeks of summer research in Physics and Astronomy.  Research projects are available both at Stony Brook University and at Brookhaven National Laboratory.  The site offers leading faculty with enthusiasm for working with undergraduates and high engagement with cutting edge research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research projects will be available in experimental, theoretical and computational tracks within the areas of: Accelerator Physics, Astronomy, Atomic Molecular and Optical Physics, Condensed Matter Physics, Cosmology, High Energy Physics and Nuclear Physics. Students will work alongside faculty on novel research projects and be given instruction in research techniques, presenting their work, and computational and experimental skills. Tutorial materials developed for the program will be made publicly available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1852143</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
