<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Young Geometric Group Theory VIII</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>28200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>28200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynsk</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is aimed at supporting U.S.-based participants at the meeting "Young Geometric Group Theory VIII" to be held at the University of the Basque Country in Bilbao, Spain, from June 30th to July 5th, 2019. Geometric group theory is an active branch of mathematics that focuses on the interactions between the geometry and topology of mathematical spaces and the algebraic objects which capture their symmetries. As most of the participants will be graduate students and early-career mathematicians, the conference will help them learn about new developments in the field, communicate their research results, and spark new research collaborations. The conference will also promote the growing diversity that geometric group theory has enjoyed through the selection of its speakers and participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference is the eighth meeting of the "Young Geometric Group Theory" series, which has been held each year since 2012. The meeting features four types of events that are designed to bring graduate students and postdocs together with early-career and well-established researchers in order to foster an environment of learning and collaboration. The events include mini courses given by four established experts in the field, plenary talks given by junior researchers, informal discussion sessions, and poster sessions and lightning talks given by graduate students. The mini courses allow graduate students and postdocs to learn cutting-edge methods in geometric group theory both from their peers and from experts. Topics range from expanders to geometric structures and representations of discrete groups. The junior talks are a way to publicize the work of young researchers and to obtain feedback and foster new collaborations.  &lt;br/&gt;A website for the conference can be found at https://sites.google.com/site/yggt2019bilbao.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1853550</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
