<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ICE-TI II</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2091668.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2091668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Regina Sievert</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to support Native-serving institutions of higher education in building their science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities. Using a suite of activities and building on past successful work, Cankdeska Cikana Community College (CCCC) addresses TCUP's goals in the project titled ICE-TI II, with the ultimate goal of increasing the number of Native Americans graduating with STEM college degrees and entering the STEM workforce. The project provides new options in CCCC's mathematics instruction through the addition of the Carnegie Math Pathways system. Through collaborative work with other tribal colleges, the math curriculum is enhanced through the integration of community and student relevant content. Improvements in student support services (such as increased Internet access and tutoring) aimed at reducing common academic and non-academic barriers to Native students? college success are also key project activities. A participatory evaluation provides feedback that enables formative optimization of the project?s activities and outcomes. Findings from the evaluation will be disseminated in a range of forums to allow others, particularly those serving Native American students, to tap into the project's lessons learned.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ICE-TI II project builds capacity in STEM instruction and research at CCCC through a comprehensive set of innovations in instruction and curriculum development. The project is designed to impact multiple system levels, including individuals, organizations, communities, and the broader society. Activities include increasing the use of problem-based learning and new educational resources, providing academic and non-academic services to ameliorate barriers to student engagement and retention, and supporting students' advancement from the two-year college experience through the transition to four-year colleges, graduate studies, and entrance into the workforce. Using Community-Based Participatory Action Research principles and employing a staggered, prospective multiple-cohort design, the project seeks to investigate questions about how best to support underprepared students? success in college. Since the Carnegie Math Pathways is a recently developed strategy, this project contributes to the emerging body of knowledge about the efficacy of CMP, especially for American Indian students and those living in rural areas. The project will inform future evaluations, as well, by assessing the psychometrics of instruments used to measure characteristics of American Indian students that may influence their academic success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1853344</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindquist</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Cynthia_Lindquist@littlehoop.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cankdeska Cikana Community College</Name>
<CityName>Fort Totten</CityName>
<ZipCode>583350269</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7017664415</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 269</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
