<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  A Dynamic Real-Time Analytics Recruiting Platform</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>749999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>749999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase II project intends to bring transparency and efficiency to the recruiting industry through a dynamic sourcing and analytics platform. Currently, it is exceedingly difficult to identify ideal candidates when recruiting for a position requiring exact criteria. The proposed platform will enable recruiters to rapidly identify optimal candidates and understand where these candidates are geographically concentrated, working, and being educated. This data-driven transparency will improve recruiter/hiring manager interactions and allow for positions to be filled more rapidly, with less productivity lost by employee turnover. The platform will highlight the most qualified candidates for a position, regardless of preconceived bias, to help uncover overlooked candidates. These efficiencies will benefit recruiters, hiring companies, individual candidates, universities, and society. Given the size of the industry ($160 billion) and the scale of inefficiencies, the project has vast commercial impact potential.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phase II research and development will be primarily focused around machine learning techniques, leveraged alongside a powerful computing framework, and applied to a substantial dataset containing billions of data points. This technology will be used to drive real-time dynamic analysis resulting in powerful recruiting analytics and ideal job candidates via interactive dashboards. Phase II will build upon the progress achieved in Phase I in the areas of machine-learning classification systems, parallel computing environments to process large quantities of data in real-time, and user-friendly visualizations. The goals of Phase II include increasing the processing power of the data architecture, modeling imputed attributes, improving the accuracy of modeling algorithms, and increasing overall interface performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1853200</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlo</FirstName>
<LastName>Martinez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>carlo@steppingblocks.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/17/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Steppingblocks, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303051754</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4782787622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3423 Piedmont Rd NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
