<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning IUCRC University of Cincinnati: Center for Hardware and Embedded System Security and Trust (CHEST)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>13375.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>13375</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dmitri Perkins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Integrated circuit and embedded hardware devices are critical to most modern military and industrial systems for defense, energy, healthcare, banking, communication, transportation, and other sectors.  These devices are more vulnerable than ever to malicious tampering by untrusted entities, with threats over a broad range of attack vectors.  Malicious functionality can be added to the devices during the design process, fabrication, or assembly, leading to compromised systems, often without detection.  This collaborative effort seeks to further the national defense by developing novel methodologies and technologies that enhance trust and security of these devices and their respective systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The to-be-planned Center is intended to enable researchers and practitioners from diverse areas -- integrated circuits, design, cryptography, system safety and resilience, etc. -- to position device security as a coherent, collaborative discipline.  It will be a hub for industry-focused research and a repository for related data.  It will foster dialog to promote advances across disciplinary boundaries.  The site will lead collaborative efforts in reverse engineering, Trojan detection at the digital parasitic level, and design for security.  It will develop attack models to better understand Trojan risks and improve detection; probabilistic Trojan detection techniques; and methods to avoid, mitigate, and protect against Trojans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center is expected to influence the design, protection, and resilience of cyber physical systems from vulnerabilities associated with device security and workforce development needed for industry, government, and military.  The Center will disseminate research results and synthesized theories on device security through multiple channels including courses taught at the six sites and professional/scholarly activities.  The results are expected to bring a significant return on investment, as they improve the readiness of industry for emergent conditions and improve resilience to frequencies, natures, and severities of threats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaborative group for the Industry &amp; University Collaborative Research for Hardware and Embedded System Security and Trust is composed of George Mason University, Northeastern University, University of Connecticut, University of Texas at Dallas, University of Virginia, and Wright State University.  The collaborators host a website at https://www.vdl.afrl.af.mil/programs/PG_CHEST_IUCRC with meeting materials, program information, publications, etc. The website is made available indefinitely or until the Center transitions to the next phase.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1854461</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Emmert</LastName>
<EmailAddress>john.emmert@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
