<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spring Institute in Noncommutative Geometry and Operator Algebras 2019</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation, particularly by graduate students and early-career researchers, in the Spring Institute in Noncommutative Geometry and Operator Algebras (NCGOA) held at Vanderbilt University from May 3, 2019 to May 9, 2019.  The award gives early-career researchers, researchers who are members of underrepresented groups, and researchers without other sources of support an opportunity to participate in this conference. The organizing committee is making efforts to recruit speakers and attendees from these groups to promote diversity.  The conference will focus on common themes and recent developments in topology, quantum algebra, topological condensed matter physics, subfactor theory, and quantum information theory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topic of the Spring 2019 NCGOA meeting will be "Algebra and Geometry Quantized and Quantified."  The conference will emphasize the interaction among operator algebras, topology, and quantum physics, in particular mathematical conformal field theory, topological condensed matter physics, and topological quantum computing.  One of the main goals of the meeting is to explore what interactions between mathematics and physics should be pursued and what paths may be open to skirt computational barriers to produce a deeper understanding of manifolds, quantum physics, subfactors and planar algebras, information theory, and complexity. NCGOA 2019 will be held in conjunction with the 34th Shanks Lecture, which will be delivered by Fields Medalist Michael Freedman.  More information can be found at https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ncgoa2019/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1855778</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
