<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fiftieth Southeastern Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 50th Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory and Computing will be held March 4-8, 2019 at Florida Atlantic University in Boca Raton. This conference has been held annually since 1970, in Baton Rouge, Louisiana and Boca Raton, Florida. The conference has grown to be the major annual event in its disciplines and plays a major role in disseminating results and in fostering collaborative work. It is not unusual for people who discuss mathematics with each other for the first time at this conference to become long-term collaborators in combinatorial research.  Its stress on the interplay among the covered topics has continued to be one of the distinctions of the conference.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hallmarks of the conference include its mixture of friendly informality and serious mathematical collaboration among participants, who traditionally include a large number of students, as well as faculty ranging from new PhDs to very senior researchers, coming from five or six continents.  There is a commitment to diversity, and wide participation by women.  All of this contributes to the strength, breadth and vitality of the international combinatorics community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference website is at http://www.math.fau.edu/combinatorics2019/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1856716</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
