<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2019 Redbud Geometry/Topology Conference</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynsk</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2019 Redbud Geometry/Topology Conference will be held April 26-28, 2019 at the University of Oklahoma. The conference will focus on topics in geometric group theory. This conference is part of an ongoing series of conferences held at universities in Arkansas and Oklahoma, intended to increase interaction and collaboration among early career and senior mathematicians in the area. It will feature prominent speakers from across North America, as well as a graduate student workshop. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2019 Redbud Geometry/Topology Conference will be centered on topics concerning mapping class groups of surfaces and CAT(0) cube complexes, and their applications to group theory and topology. The invited speakers are Juliette Bavard (Universite de Rennes), Mladen Bestvina (University of Utah), Michelle Chu (UC Santa Barbara), Jingyin Huang (Ohio State University), Kasia Jankiewicz (University of Chicago), Daniel Margalit (Georgia Tech), Andrew Putman (University of Notre Dame), Yulan Qing (University of Toronto), and Balazs Strenner (Georgia Tech). The conference begins with a workshop designed to enhance the experience of graduate students and junior researchers. The workshop will feature expository talks by Bestvina, Huang, and Putman. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference website: http://www.math.ou.edu/redbud/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1856678</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
